<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Fragmenta poetica, or, Miscelanies of poetical musings, moral and divine by Nich. Murford.</title>
            <author>Murford, Nicholas, fl. 1638-1652.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1650</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 172 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 45 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A51621</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M3100</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R36607</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">15742885</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 15742885</idno>
            <idno type="VID">104586</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A51621)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 104586)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1153:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Fragmenta poetica, or, Miscelanies of poetical musings, moral and divine by Nich. Murford.</title>
                  <author>Murford, Nicholas, fl. 1638-1652.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[18], 65, [1] p., [1] leaf of plates : port.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Humphrey Moseley ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1650.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Contains portrait frontispiece.</note>
                  <note>Includes index.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:104586:1"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <lg>
                     <l>He that Views Murfords face, sees but a Ray</l>
                     <l>Of light reflected, or a glympse of day</l>
                     <l>But he that reads his Arras woven line</l>
                     <l>C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>n templates Phoebus as he brightly shine</l>
                  </lg>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:104586:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Fragmenta Poëtica:</hi> OR, MISCELANIES OF POETICAL MUSINGS, Moral and Divine: BY <hi>NICH. M<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RFORD.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>tque artes pariat ſolertia, nutriat uſus. <bibl>
                     <hi>Claud.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </l>
               <l>Ad Coelum volito, ut in Deo quieſcam.</l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Humphrey Moſeley,</hi> at the ſigne of the Prince's Arms in S. <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard. 1650.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:104586:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:104586:2"/>
            <head>To the READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Courteous Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hether Engliſh reſident in the Netherlands; Netherlander enjoying the benefit of the Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Tongue; or Domestick Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh; (for it may light into the hands of all ſorts of you) I intreat firſt your judicious rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, and then your favourable cenſuring of this ſmall Poem: And lay not pride, or ſauci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs unto its charge, becauſe it walks into the world before ſome of its elder brethren; for as the noble <hi>S. Theodore de Mayern</hi> ſaid in his Epistle before the <hi>Inſectorum ſive mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morum animalium theatrum,</hi> of learned <hi>Moufet,</hi> who was neer of my name, of the ſame Countrey, (France) and perhaps of my kindred; (for bloud, as rivers, run into many places (high and low) and yet came from one and the ſame fountain; and ebbs of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes ſometimes cauſe falſe Orthography in one and the ſame name) ſpeaking of the ſaid Books, laying dormant in his ſtudy, attributes it <hi>Typographorum inhiantium culpae;</hi> And in the ſame Epiſtle to the ſaid Poſthume Work, he exclames, <hi>O tempora, in quibus
<pb facs="tcp:104586:3"/>
eruditorum hominum ſudores, ex pretio operis ſolvendo, &amp; aere, in charta, &amp; atra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mento comparandis locando, vel ex vulgi (peſſimis ut plurimùm applaudentis) depra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vato ſenſu, non ex rei eſſentia, vel ſubjecti dignitate, aut ſolida ejuſdem explanatione aeſtimantur!</hi> And indeed, if any ſolidity appears in a Book, the Vulgar ſay, it ſmels too much of Anchoriſm; but I ſay of thoſe Books that are all compacted of whimſies, they are like Briſtol ſtones, not valued by a judicious Jeweller, and as one wittily obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved on a fooliſh Book, to which was written <hi>Finis,</hi>
               <q>
                  <l>—Nay, there thou lieſt my friend:</l>
                  <l>In writing fooliſh Books there is no end.</l>
               </q>
But (I am made to believe) that as this ſmal Pamphlet is not wholly void of ſome holy Sonnets; ſo it is not wholly without ſome (not unprofitable) Satyrs, &amp;c. Wherefore I hope the Stationers ſhall have no cauſe to ſigh out, <hi>It will not ſell!</hi> To conclude, Reader, I wiſh thee as much pleaſure in the reading, as I had in the writing of it.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Pray, and Fare-well.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="encomium">
            <div type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:104586:3"/>
               <head>Precatio Authoris!</head>
               <l>DIc mihi quid ſcribam! da tu mihi vota vovenda!</l>
               <l>Sic bene ſemper agam, ſic bona vota mea.</l>
               <l>Gratia ſit ſervo ad ſervatum juſſa beata!</l>
               <l>Ille beatus enim, qui tua juſſa facit.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>L'Auteur au Lecteur de ſon ouvre.</head>
               <l>Petit Livre, faicte moy e'la ſervice</l>
               <l>Monſtrer l'Anglois la vertu par la vice;</l>
               <l>Mon Dieu, &amp; mon maiſtre ſon nom eſlever,</l>
               <l>Faicte devoir donner tout l'honeur.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Idem ad eundem.</head>
               <l>My little Book, pray doe me the ſmall ſervice</l>
               <l>To ſhew <hi>England</hi> true vertue by meer vice;</l>
               <l>T'extoll my God, and Maſters name above,</l>
               <l>Strive thou my Soul in praisfull ſtrains to move!</l>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Den Wenſch.</head>
               <l>Och dat myn Boecrken Engel-landt nu moghen</l>
               <l>Volle maken Engel-ghelyk menſchen,</l>
               <l>En ick ghelyk een Engel hoogh ghebore,</l>
               <l>Moghen te ſchrieven als ſanctus Paulus fore!</l>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>To the Author.</head>
               <l>EV'n as the naſty Swine both flies and hates</l>
               <l>All fragrant Ointments; (for what recreates</l>
               <l>Our ſenſes unto them is peſtilent.)</l>
               <l>Juſt ſo of thy ſtrong lines the very ſent</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:104586:4"/>Will make the Boriſh Ruſticks ſcud amain,</l>
               <l>Never deſiring to read Verſe again.</l>
               <l>Let Hinds baſe things admire. May <hi>Phoebus</hi> ſtill</l>
               <l>Thy cups full of <hi>Caſtalian</hi> liquor fill</l>
               <l>Up to the brim; for them that can Compoſe</l>
               <l>Like Thee, the Muſes darling: unto thoſe</l>
               <l>I leave—</l>
               <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <hi>Ralph Piggott.</hi> 
                     <abbr>Eſq</abbr>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon the Authors Poems.</head>
               <l>WHere's the beſt Inn? here Reader: Stay</l>
               <l>Pray, light and drink: What, haſte away?</l>
               <l>Here's Attick Juncates; and for Wine,</l>
               <l>Nectar both Morall and Divine.</l>
               <l>Take mine Hoſt's proffer: 'Tis a crime</l>
               <l>Not to be drunk with Extatick rime.</l>
               <closer>
                  <signed>J. A.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>On the Authors mixt Poems.</head>
               <l>WHat is't you want? Wit or Wine?</l>
               <l>Fancies Morall or Divine?</l>
               <l>Read theſe Poems: what you crave,</l>
               <l>You can no ſooner ask, then have.</l>
               <closer>
                  <signed>O. B.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Nich. Murford Authori Hoſpiti Amiciſſimo.</head>
               <l>I Hugg thy Fancy much, becauſe Divine;</l>
               <l>Nature is excellent in its refine.</l>
               <l>Divine Raptures, are, Natures complements,</l>
               <l>And gives perfection to mixt Elements.</l>
               <l>And ſince mine Hoſt can reach heaven with a rime</l>
               <l>I'll honour only Sack, Nectar ſublime:</l>
               <l>And pray a bleſſing to the Authors pains</l>
               <l>In heav'n immortall, on earth honeſt gains.</l>
               <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <hi>Owen Barne,</hi> Gent.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:104586:4"/>
               <head>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon the Authors Work.</head>
               <l>Thy curious Miſcellanies of delight,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hall be Wits off-ſpring, Art's Hermaphrodite.</l>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Idem.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon his Inne.</head>
               <l>Your Inn's the Star, but from your ſelf the Beam</l>
               <l>Of Light, to it, as from the Sun doth ſtream.</l>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Idem.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Or thus,</head>
               <l>No more the Star ſhall be to me</l>
               <l>Of ſuch an Inn a ſigne, but Thee.</l>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Idem.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>To the Reader of thoſe Poems.</head>
               <l>Hoſpitis in menſa, vultum non fercula penſa.</l>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Idem.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Ad Authorem.</head>
               <l>ALma tibi mater fuit Anglia, Gallia nutrix,</l>
               <l>Et Germana dehinc hospita tellus erat.</l>
               <l>Hinc tres ſermones retines, veluti genuinos,</l>
               <l>Romanum quartum lectio multa dedit.</l>
               <l>Addidit ingenium praeſtans natura, ſic ortus</l>
               <l>Es vates Lauro dignus Apollineâ;</l>
               <l>Sed quod divinum reſonat tua Muſa Poëma</l>
               <l>Omnes mirantur, quod ſuper Aſtra volas;</l>
               <l>Nec mirum, non dat Tellus, Naturavè Mentem,</l>
               <l>Coelitus emiſſa haec, ſydera ſumma petit.</l>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Tho. Parkin, <hi>Medicinae Doctor.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Engliſhed.</head>
               <l>THy Mother <hi>England</hi> was, thy Nurſe was <hi>France,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Duitzlandt</hi> thine Hoſteſs. Hence thou didſt inhance</l>
               <l>Three native Tongues; then Induſtry begot</l>
               <l>Latin the fourth. Thy wit by Nature's lot</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:104586:5"/>Was ſuch, that thou a Poet maſculine</l>
               <l>Becam'ſt by drinking <hi>Helicon</hi> divine.</l>
               <l>But that thy Muſe ſo ſacred is, and high,</l>
               <l>Men marvell thou ſhouldſt mount above the Skie;</l>
               <l>No marvell: Place, nor Nature Thee ſoul gave,</l>
               <l>From Heav'n it came, and Heav'n again doth crave</l>
               <closer>
                  <signed>T. P.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Au Lecteur.</head>
               <l>Chanſons plein de ſens,</l>
               <l>Oraiſons plein d'encens;</l>
               <l>Poeſie, &amp; Pieté</l>
               <l>Sont inſemble icy.</l>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Tho. Parkin.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>To his worthy Friend Mr. <hi>N.M.</hi> Merchant, on his <hi>Fragmenta Poetica,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</head>
               <l>NOt to applaud when deſert makes it due,</l>
               <l>Hath as deep ſhare in ill, as to avow</l>
               <l>The Act (by not reproving it) ſeen done,</l>
               <l>Such were my <hi>Errour,</hi> O Poëtick Son</l>
               <l>Of <hi>Pallas,</hi> if I don't (peruſing) praiſe</l>
               <l>Thy touring raptures, meriting rich Bayes.</l>
               <l>Good <hi>Nich,</hi> march on; May thy quaint head-piece ſhine</l>
               <l>As Limbeck of thoſe learned ſiſters Nine!</l>
               <l>The cordiall Vote of a True friend of thine.</l>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Nich. Toll, Paſtor at Lynn.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:104586:5"/>
               <head>To the Author.</head>
               <l>WHen whole-ſale Men are bankrupt, &amp; none left</l>
               <l>To trade in wit, but thoſe who do't by theft;</l>
               <l>Such as retail rime weekly by a ſheet,</l>
               <l>To gain perhaps the Counter or the Fleet:</l>
               <l>In ſuch a Fancy-famin not to raiſe,</l>
               <l>But make wit cheap; deſerves a double Bayes.</l>
               <l>This thou haſt done in theſe thy works, nay more;</l>
               <l>For thou haſt brought <hi>Pernaſſus</hi> to our ſhore;</l>
               <l>Salt Owſe a freſh Muſe has, when <hi>Cam's</hi> are ſalt;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Lyn</hi> has a capering Nymph, when <hi>Oxford's</hi> halt:</l>
               <l>Warehouſe of Wit, fill ſtill; let others gain,</l>
               <l>By fetching Fortunes goods from <hi>France</hi> or <hi>Spain!</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Thou haſt a higher trade, which none o'them uſes;</l>
               <l>Thy ſtock is verſe, thy factors are the Muſes,</l>
               <l>Thy returns Fame; thine is ſuch Merchandize,</l>
               <l>As feeds not Cuſtom, and quite ſtarves Excize:</l>
               <l>Trade on wits Merchant, give the world to know</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Chaucer</hi> was bred in <hi>Lyn,</hi> and ſo wert Thou.</l>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Raptim <hi>Tho. Toll junior,</hi> Gent.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>To the Author Mr. <hi>N.M.</hi> upon his divine POEMS.</head>
               <l>COmmend thy Verſe ſweet NICH? I need not! tuſh,</l>
               <l>When Wines are good, they never want a Buſh.</l>
               <l>Commend thy Verſe? I cannot! 'tis a Task</l>
               <l>To doe it well, would <hi>Cleavelands</hi> Fancy ask;</l>
               <l>Yet this Ile ſpeak for thy immortall credit,</l>
               <l>It is no ſpurious piece: but MURFORD did it.</l>
               <l>At theſe thy Lines, whos'er ſhall take offence,</l>
               <l>They underſtand them not, they have no ſenſe.</l>
               <l>Let who will cavill at thy Book, what's in't</l>
               <l>Is not imperfect; but 'tis done in PRINT.</l>
               <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <hi>Tho. Leech,</hi> A.M.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:104586:6"/>
               <l>GO thou away with all the praiſe of mine,</l>
               <l>Who Own'ſt theſe Poems Morall and Divine.</l>
               <l>What? canſt not doe enough, but over-do't,</l>
               <l>Draw us ſuch Wine, ſo good, and Sugar to't?</l>
               <l>Let others brows be crowned with a ruſh,</l>
               <l>The Lawrel's thine; yet this Wine needs no Buſh.</l>
               <l>Thy Star's a glorious Sun, and gives more light</l>
               <l>Then can b'obſcur'd by fouleſt envies ſpight.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>To his eſteemed friend M. <hi>Nich. Murford,</hi> On his <hi>Fragmenta Poetica.</hi>
               </head>
               <l>THat <hi>Memnons</hi> image tuned by the heat</l>
               <l>Of glitt'ring rayes ſhowr'd down fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <hi>Titans</hi> ſeat</l>
               <l>Prov'd Vocal, I'le not doubt, ſince ſparks of wit</l>
               <l>And Scintillations of thy brain made fit</l>
               <l>Our indiſpoſed Fancies, to produce</l>
               <l>Impreſſions propagated from thy Muſe.</l>
               <l>For thoſe Poetick flames in us begun,</l>
               <l>Are all derivative from thee our Sun.</l>
               <l>That humane ſouls are Numbers as of old</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Xenocrates</hi> affirm'd, is now controll'd,</l>
               <l>Since thine ſuch rare endowments doth poſſeſs,</l>
               <l>Which are both Singular, and Numberleſs;</l>
               <l>Yet why goe I about thus to confine</l>
               <l>Thy boundleſs praiſe to th'compaſs of a Line,</l>
               <l>Which he that would expreſs, and make it known,</l>
               <l>Muſt write a Volume larger then thine own:</l>
               <l>Let this ſuffice, that we adorn thy praiſe</l>
               <l>Now, not with Ivy, but Immortall Bayes.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:104586:6"/>
               <head>To the Book.</head>
               <l>THou <hi>Pallas</hi> vented from moſt pregnant brains,</l>
               <l>Go, teach the world new Mathematick ſtrains;</l>
               <l>This little Quadrature to us imparts</l>
               <l>The Circle of all Sciences and Arts.</l>
               <l>Thoſe ſcandalizing pens which at thee wonder,</l>
               <l>Shall know, that <hi>Bacchus</hi> was begot with thunder.</l>
               <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <hi>J. Baſtard.</hi> A. B.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>To his worthy friend M. <hi>Nich. Murford,</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon his <hi>Fragmenta Poetica.</hi>
               </head>
               <l>IN Faith I wonder, yet in Truth I ſee,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Pallas</hi> will leave the Univerſitie,</l>
               <l>And come to <hi>Lynn;</hi> ſhe hath already ſent</l>
               <l>Her head-piece to thy houſe, her ſacred tent,</l>
               <l>Which is a ſign ſhe'll come. Affirm who dare</l>
               <l>A man i' th' Moon to be, he's in the Starre,</l>
               <l>Whoſe drink's no White, nor Claret, no ſuch meane,</l>
               <l>He drinks not Hippocras, but Hippocrene;</l>
               <l>Whoſe radiant ſplendour, whoſe quaint courteous uſes</l>
               <l>Make him an Hoſt fit for the thrice three muſes.</l>
               <l>Mourn then ye Heliconian Brats, give o're</l>
               <l>Your wonted wanton Garbs, inveſt no more</l>
               <l>Your Selves with colours diapred; put on</l>
               <l>Sable accoutrement, <hi>Pallas</hi> is gone.</l>
               <l>No news, alas; that wit would ſoon decay,</l>
               <l>Who knew not, when the head was ta'ne away?</l>
               <l>The ſacred brains muſt putrifie we know,</l>
               <l>Seeing the <hi>Pia Mater</hi>'s wounded ſo.</l>
               <l>Star-gazers, have your wits ſequeſtred been,</l>
               <l>As well as wealth, that none this Star have ſeen?</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:104586:7"/>It neither riſe nor fals, that ye may know it,</l>
               <l>It hangs o're <hi>Helicon,</hi> go quickly to it:</l>
               <l>Where you ſhall finde him, whom you'l ſwear to be</l>
               <l>Natures perfection, Wits Epitome.</l>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Sic obteſtatur <hi>Tuiſſimus Carolus Cromer, Cantabr. Coll. Corp. Chriſti.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>To his very good Friend Mr. <hi>Nich. Murford,</hi> upon his POEMS.</head>
               <l>DEar Friend, I'll ſwear thy Verſes I muſt call</l>
               <l>Not ſublunary, but Celeſtiall;</l>
               <l>For ſure th'Intelligences mov'd thy brain,</l>
               <l>And were the <hi>primum mobile</hi> of thy ſtrain</l>
               <l>In Poëtry; thou doſt ſo ſweetly ſing,</l>
               <l>That wer't not Treaſon, I'd proclaim thee King</l>
               <l>In <hi>Homer's</hi> ſtead; and could I have my will.</l>
               <l>Thou ſhouldſt be chief of all the bifork'd Hill.</l>
               <l>Thy head that Capitol of wiſdom too,</l>
               <l>Does more then Nature, much as Art can do.</l>
               <l>Thy <hi>Starre</hi> works great effects of Chimiſtrie,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Aurum</hi> it make's to ſome <hi>Potabile;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>It alſo wonders works upon Mens Wits,</l>
               <l>And makes them think the lower Orb hath fits</l>
               <l>Of th'trembling Ague, and they'll ſwear by <hi>Jove,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Copernicus</hi> ſpeaks true, the Earth does move;</l>
               <l>And for thy Book, the praiſe it gets of mine,</l>
               <l>Is only this, it's exc'lent good, and Thine.</l>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Tho. Parkin, junior. A. B.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:104586:7"/>
               <head>Upon the pithy Poems of Mr. <hi>Nicholas Murford,</hi> MERCHANT.</head>
               <l>I Do not here appear to praiſe thy Book,</l>
               <l>Becauſe I have acquaintance with Thee took.</l>
               <l>I doe not praiſe thy Book, becauſe of Thee;</l>
               <l>But praiſe Thee for thy witty Book, all ſee.</l>
               <l>Merchant of wit, who tradeſt in it much,</l>
               <l>And ſell'ſt to ſuch, to buy that doe not grutch,</l>
               <l>Thy <hi>German, French,</hi> and <hi>Belgick</hi> voy'ages; none</l>
               <l>Can be compar'd to this, to <hi>Helicon:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Ah! what great pity was it, that ſuch Wit</l>
               <l>Did never in an <hi>Academy</hi> ſit?</l>
               <l>For if thou hadſt, what had been ancient blades?</l>
               <l>Thou hadſt out-done great <hi>Homer's Iliads:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Yet notwithſtanding, oh! how thou doſt ſhame</l>
               <l>Some that from learned <hi>Ox,</hi> and <hi>Cam</hi> have came?</l>
               <l>When thou writ'ſt to thy Book, thy Friends, thy God,</l>
               <l>How is thy ſoaring <hi>Pegaſus</hi> then ſhod!</l>
               <l>When thou haſt lad'n thy Ships, <hi>&amp; caetera,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Then <hi>nulla dies ſine linea.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Thy witty, wholſome <hi>Satyrs</hi> laſh not men;</l>
               <l>But heart-corrupting, and Soul-wounding ſin.</l>
               <l>When thou art pleas'd to write upon thine Inn,</l>
               <l>Raſh men think no man e're in ſuch came in:</l>
               <l>But to the <hi>STAR</hi> thy Tavern, if men come,</l>
               <l>The firſt words are, Is the good man at home?</l>
               <l>And then (with much reſpect) moſt happy he</l>
               <l>Who hath thy moſt delightfull companie.</l>
               <l>Never did I ſee man ſo much reſpected</l>
               <l>In ſuch a calling, one ſo perfected!</l>
               <l>In brief, if one would praiſe Thee, it is thus,</l>
               <l>The Author is, <hi>Vnus in omnibus.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Thy Book repleat is with Wits purity,</l>
               <l>Full of Divine wit; but no ſurquedry.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:104586:8"/>
                  <hi>Caeſar,</hi> if not <hi>Caeſar,</hi> would wiſh to bee</l>
               <l>(I verily do think) <hi>like unto Thee.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>(As <hi>Alexander</hi> ſaid t' <hi>Diogenes</hi>)</l>
               <l>God help poor Kings, they ha'nt ſuch happy days!</l>
               <l>If thou abuſed art by a dul Elf,</l>
               <l>Thou'lt jeer him ſo, he'll chuſe to hang himſelf,</l>
               <l>As once did one of old. Thus theſe thy laies</l>
               <l>Ingag'd me Secretary of thy praiſe,</l>
               <l>And thou deſerveſt to be Secretary</l>
               <l>To England's beſt, and gallantſt Noble, marry.</l>
               <closer>
                  <signed>J. B.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>A l' Autheur.</head>
               <l>MOn melieur Amy (pluſtoſt) ma foy</l>
               <l>Vouz merite Secretaire du Roy.</l>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Robert Thorowgood <hi>Merchant.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>To the Authour M. <hi>Nicholas Murford,</hi> Merchant. <hi>Nurs-child of Maro. <hi>Anag.</hi>
                  </hi>
               </head>
               <l>THy Poems on a Pillory makes me ſtand</l>
               <l>With both my ears faſt nail'd, and fixed hand</l>
               <l>Upon thy Book, which took me when I ſee't</l>
               <l>(As flies are taken) fetter'd by the feet</l>
               <l>Of thy ſmooth verſe. Thou, whoſe ſmooth chin doth write</l>
               <l>Thy date of years the houres of day and night,</l>
               <l>That abler wits admire to ſee thee climbe</l>
               <l>To ſo great height in ſuch ſhort ſpace of time.</l>
               <l>Poetrie's now grown Staple-Merchandize</l>
               <l>Free from Old Cuſtome or the New Exciſe.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Silveſter, Spenſer, Johnſonn, Draiton, Donn,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>May ſee Verſe meaſured by the Laſt and Tunn,</l>
               <l>While Dutch, French, Spaniſh, Engliſh liquours uſe</l>
               <l>T' adorn thy houſe, their learnings grace thy Muſe;</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:104586:8"/>Thy frolique Nimble Genius like thy Star</l>
               <l>That twinckling brings the Magi from afar</l>
               <l>Into theſe Northern parts to come to Lynne</l>
               <l>To ſee two Rarities, thy Works, thy Inne,</l>
               <l>Which with thy Star and Stable repreſent</l>
               <l>A ſecond Bethlem. Next comes ſweet Content:</l>
               <l>When men were wiſe and happy, then this Theam</l>
               <l>Was welcome news, that now ſeems but a dream.</l>
               <l>The ancient Bards reſerv'd this diſh of meat</l>
               <l>For Kings to taſte on: then were Crowns compleat.</l>
               <l>But ſince their learned days Content and Kings</l>
               <l>Are from us fled with their high-towring wings</l>
               <l>Not ſeen, felt, heard, or underſtood, Unleſſe</l>
               <l>That in a Gallie, this a game at Cheſſe.</l>
               <l>Thy Muſe hath made thee Momus-free, each word</l>
               <l>Mur'd with a Wall, and Moted with a Ford,</l>
               <l>Thus garriſon'd, in this the Nectar flows,</l>
               <l>In that the Lawrel ſprings to binde thy Brows.</l>
               <l>Let the poor Scoundrel praiſe the poor-patcht words</l>
               <l>Of ebrious Poets ſheets, ſung on two bords</l>
               <l>Upon a pair of Truſſels in a Fair,</l>
               <l>Or Market, where the Clowns and Girles repair;</l>
               <l>And let the Romancer his ſtories gild</l>
               <l>With Ladies loves, Knights conq'ring, Giants kild.</l>
               <l>Let the bold weekſ-man write his wrong-ſet news,</l>
               <l>That may by Patent all the world abuſe,</l>
               <l>With ſix days works of new-created lies</l>
               <l>To binde up Gally-pots and bottome pies.</l>
               <l>Let them ſeek praiſes where they will for mee,</l>
               <l>All that I have or can, belong to thee,</l>
               <l>And to thy Star that calculates thy fate</l>
               <l>To be divine <hi>Apollo</hi>'s right-hand mate,</l>
               <l>And make me wiſh my ſelf a Star, to bee</l>
               <l>A pointer in the Guoards to ſay <hi>that's Hee.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">☞</note>
               </l>
               <l>And for thy Book, let never greaſie thumb,</l>
               <l>Nor ſhallow-brain upon thy pages come,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:104586:9"/>Nor doults that muſt be forc'd to read it twice,</l>
               <l>Nor ignorance attempt to ask the price,</l>
               <l>Nor ſtammering fools, that hack and mar the ſence,</l>
               <l>The ſellers power's repeal'd to take their pence;</l>
               <l>Thy worthy Work ſhall make thy Pen ſo fam'd,</l>
               <l>And get thee glory that thy Book's <hi>Nick-nam'd.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Then march-on MURFORD never be afraid,</l>
               <l>The Muſes love t'have young beginners trade;</l>
               <l>And I ſhort to expreſs thy worth, thy rime,</l>
               <l>Crave leave to end and mend another time.</l>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Jo. Bradford.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>To my exceedingly reſpected friend Mr. <hi>Nicholas M<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RFORD,</hi> Merchant.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>WHen Reaſon, Fancy, Wit, and Grace</l>
                  <l>In tender years take each their place,</l>
                  <l>Theſe make the man. All theſe I ſee.</l>
                  <l>Concur in this thy Book, and Thee.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thou Merchant <hi>Murford</hi> maiſt be well,</l>
                  <l>For this thy Book doth much excell,</l>
                  <l>And ſet's forth Reaſon, Wit, and Grace</l>
                  <l>In every line, in their due place.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Good Friend, hold on, and write a-gain;</l>
                  <l>This Book will ſell, and thou'lt remain</l>
                  <l>Incourag'd ſtill for future Wark,</l>
                  <l>And get the name of <hi>learned Clark.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>E're long thou'lt hear men will relate</l>
                  <l>Thee to be Poët laureate.</l>
                  <l>Thus think I of thy Book, and Thee,</l>
                  <l>And am thy faithfull friend and free.</l>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>W. Skynner,</hi> Gent.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </lg>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb facs="tcp:104586:9"/>
            <head>The Invocation. <hi>To the moſt High GOD.</hi> His humble Servant Implores his moſt favourable aſſiſtance.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>OH all-wiſe God! with the leaſt word who can</l>
               <l>Make me dull wretch, as clear as <hi>Solomon;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Daign from the Orbs to view this Work of mine,</l>
               <l>And with Diviner raptures it refine?</l>
               <l>Great God! I crave thy Spirit, and doe refuſe</l>
               <l>To this my Work to invocate a Muſe.</l>
               <l>"A ſacred heat inſpires my Soul to try</l>
               <l>If Verſe can give me what baſe Earth deny,</l>
               <l>A true content; therefore (Lord!) I'll think on</l>
               <l>"Thy <hi>Jordan</hi> for my pureſt <hi>Helicon;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>"And for bifork'd <hi>Pernaſſus,</hi> I will ſet</l>
               <l>"My fancy on thy ſacred <hi>Olivet;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>For thy Diviner Poet <hi>David</hi> did</l>
               <l>That which was ne're attain'd to by <hi>Ovid.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Nay thou who <hi>Aetna</hi> curb'ſt, and the wilde Sea,</l>
               <l>Shalt of my Songs be <hi>Alpha</hi> and <hi>Omega.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Let my Divine things be perspicuous,</l>
               <l>And ev'n my worſt (my God) be vertuous!</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:104586:10"/>Let me have holy fraud: with roundelaies</l>
               <l>Let inter-mixed be moſt ſacred laies!</l>
               <l>Let my but moral things have vertue on,</l>
               <l>And my Divine have pure Religion!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Let my wit draw the Reader with ſuch Art,</l>
               <l>That Grace may ſweetly captivate his Heart!</l>
               <l>Oh let my Epigrams jeer him from bad,</l>
               <l>My Satyrs make him to leave vice be glad!</l>
               <l>My Elegies to make him mourn for's folly,</l>
               <l>My holy Sonnets learn him to be holy!</l>
               <l>"Grant Verſe may finde him; who a Sermon flies,</l>
               <l>"And turn delight into a ſacrifice!</l>
               <l>Let me not be like thoſe live ill, preach well,</l>
               <l>Who ſave mens ſouls; yet ſend their own to Hell!</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:104586:10"/>
            <head>POEMS. The STORM and CALM: <hi>Sent from Embden to M.</hi> Edw. Ma. <hi>and M.</hi> Tho. Ly.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>WEary with Reading and with Meditation,</l>
               <l>Upon my ſpirit ſetled a Vexation:</l>
               <l>Having no Compaſs, nor no Chard to view,</l>
               <l>Sith we did onely drive, and over-view,</l>
               <l>What did our haſtie ſpirits Griefs renew,</l>
               <l>I thought in Verſe to parley once with you.</l>
               <l>The ſometime-mounting Sea is now ſo calm,</l>
               <l>As if it were ſurprized with a qualm:</l>
               <l>The wanton Sails do beat the quiet Maſte,</l>
               <l>And the Sun's heat doth make Wood pitch to taſte:</l>
               <l>Two days before I gave the land-ſight ſhilling,</l>
               <l>Which I to give, as they to take was willing,</l>
               <l>The Mariners were almoſt at a ſtrife</l>
               <l>To have me hear what each would ſay to's wife.</l>
               <l>The thieviſh Iriſh we had quite giv'n over,</l>
               <l>Concerning thoughts that they could us diſcover:</l>
               <l>We anchor'd with Hope's anchor, and our own;</l>
               <l>Then from the ground they both again were ſhown.</l>
               <l>Now a diſſembling voice of winde doth ſpeak;</l>
               <l>But preſently we cannot hear him ſqueak.</l>
               <l>The ſleepie Sea that 'fore ſo boiſt'rous was,</l>
               <l>Is now as ſmoothe as the moſt even Glaſs:</l>
               <l>One now would think the water to be dead,</l>
               <l>Or with dead ſleep to be heavie as Lead;</l>
               <l>Which not to wake, the ſtormy folk I cry-on;</l>
               <l>"O 'tis not good to wake a ſleeping Lion!</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:104586:11"/>For not long ſince, in the ſame ſhip we were,</l>
               <l>When the mad Winde I thought would tear her gear;</l>
               <l>And carrying by th' board a Maſte, might quail</l>
               <l>The ſtouteſt heart; the skeening of a Sail,</l>
               <l>The ſhipping of a Sea, the Deck in water</l>
               <l>For full five hours in my conceit was greater:</l>
               <l>But all together, in my vainer minde,</l>
               <l>Would make a man to fear the raging winde:</l>
               <l>And if the Winde, which was but God's meer Creature,</l>
               <l>O how much more God, who was the Creator!</l>
               <l>But when the Ship was like to over-ſet,</l>
               <l>The Sea-men's eyes were dry, though bodies wet.</l>
               <l>In ſtead of praying, ſome did curſes vent;</l>
               <l>Which that they did, I would they might repent.</l>
               <l>Titan withdrew his golden locks; our Ark</l>
               <l>Now in the day muſt wander in the dark.</l>
               <l>One time we think we muſt for Norway go;</l>
               <l>Then for Scotland; then neither is it ſo;</l>
               <l>For we have hopes for Tinmouth, then for Humber:</l>
               <l>Thus doubtful fears our doubtful ſouls incumber.</l>
               <l>So dang'rous was our Voyage, that I vow,</l>
               <l>I love your preſence, but woul'n't have it now.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thus have we here the calm Proſperity,</l>
               <l>And the great ſtorm of fierce Adverſity;</l>
               <l>Which I deſire to draw to uſe: a Moral</l>
               <l>May here drawn out be for us mortals all.</l>
               <l>The firſt, her Sun, will take away our cloke,</l>
               <l>Before the other's bluſtring winde can choke.</l>
               <l>In Court Eliſha had need doubly have</l>
               <l>Elijah's ſpirit, who was in the wave</l>
               <l>Of ſoul-trying, yet good Adverſity,</l>
               <l>Which is the heav'nly Univerſity.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Oh Lord, give me my portion of theſe,</l>
               <l>Or either, as thou think fit, and doſt pleaſe.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <head>To the Right Worſhipful <hi>Thomas Revet</hi> Maior elect of <hi>Kings Lynn. The PRESENT.</hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <l>WHile wealthy Senators, and Burghers rich,</l>
               <l>Make privie ſearch th'row th'Ocean and each ditch</l>
               <l>For curious, rarer, and ſcarce heard of Fiſhes,</l>
               <l>With Love and Pride to furniſh your vaſt diſhes;</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:104586:11"/>And neighb'ring Knights and Gentry hunt each Park,</l>
               <l>Search Fields and all for th' nimble Deer i'th' dark,</l>
               <l>Ere that Aurora hath her treſſes dighted,</l>
               <l>Or Phoſpher hath the Hemiſphere belighted,</l>
               <l>The winged creatures with obſervant eye</l>
               <l>Watching, and waiting if they can eſpie:</l>
               <l>While theſe (having obtain'd) offer their Preſents,</l>
               <l>My Muſe their way doth wave, and not reſents;</l>
               <l>But for King John's Cup, brings Nectar ſublime,</l>
               <l>And (for one diſh) Ambroſia divine.</l>
               <l>And if you Muſick affect and admire,</l>
               <l>Apollo ſhall deſcend with his ſweet Lyre.</l>
               <l>The Muſes ſhall with trenchers wait upon you,</l>
               <l>If there chance not to be ſervants enough;</l>
               <l>Nay, I'll diſpeople Air, Sea, and the Earth,</l>
               <l>Rather (dear Sir) then there ſhould be a dearth</l>
               <l>At your great Feſtival; and could I charm,</l>
               <l>None ſhould in thought, word, deed, produce you harm:</l>
               <l>And I hope (Sir) you'll pleaſe for to give way</l>
               <l>To hear a Poet Prophet turn, and pray.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>May Envie ſleep under your foot! Oh, may</l>
               <l>Your yeer of charge ſeem as one joyful day!</l>
               <l>May we Plebeans with true Love, not Hate,</l>
               <l>Obey your juſt commands, as you the State!</l>
               <l>May you have Conſcience, and have Policie,</l>
               <l>Before this People to walk prudently!</l>
               <l>May your two houſes have one ſingle heart,</l>
               <l>And (Solon-like) to govern well, the Art!</l>
               <l>May the great God's receivers, ev'n the Poor,</l>
               <l>Reliev'd be at their houſes, and your door!</l>
               <l>May Lyn ſtill flouriſh, and increaſe by Trade,</l>
               <l>Ploughing the Ocean with the Naval blade!</l>
               <l>May Spain, France, Belgia, Germany,</l>
               <l>Our flood of fortunes ev'n like Venice ſpy!</l>
               <l>May Alms ſupport the ag'd, may Trades the youth,</l>
               <l>And may your praiſes be ſpake by each mouth!</l>
               <l>May children (yet unborn) ſay REVET did</l>
               <l>All that was good, in nothing he miſdid!</l>
               <l>That to your mem'ry there may be regard,</l>
               <l>When Death upon you place a <hi>Corps du guard.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Nay ſtay: for I ha'n't done (Sir;) here's not all:</l>
               <l>For here's a Feaſt you'll ſay's Poetical:</l>
               <l>But could men's cordial and their often wiſhes</l>
               <l>Supply your Board, then you ſhould have theſe diſhes:</l>
               <l>And to ſpeak truth, of old they were no babies</l>
               <l>Who us'd this ſaying, <hi>Crede quòd habes, &amp; habes.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:104586:12"/>
               <head>Firſt Courſe.</head>
               <l>Collars of Brawn, ſtiff like a well-ſtarch'd Ruff,</l>
               <l>Sallet, and Capon boyld tender enough,</l>
               <l>Gurnet, and Mallard, after the ſame ſort,</l>
               <l>With a forc'd boyld meat, ordered with port;</l>
               <l>A roſted Neats-tongue, with a Pudding in it,</l>
               <l>(Ev'n ſuch a tongue as ne'r did uſe to ſin it.)</l>
               <l>A made diſh of Puff-paſte, with a fair Shoulder-</l>
               <l>Of Mutton ô-leaves, capers 'fore the houlder.</l>
               <l>A Chine of Beef, Chewets of weak-brain'd Veal,</l>
               <l>A Sican, an Olive-Pye, a Pig ſha'nt ſqueal.</l>
               <l>A leg of Mutton, Lark-pye, and a Turky,</l>
               <l>With Ven'ſon-Paſty, Capon, Cuſtard work I,</l>
               <l>And ha'nt the leaſt remorſe,</l>
               <l>Or thought o' th' ſecond Courſe.</l>
               <l>Now I have time, and now with all my force,</l>
               <l>I'll muſter up my wiſhed ſecond Courſe.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Second Courſe.</head>
               <l>A tender Kidd, with a couple of Rabbits;</l>
               <l>A Kickſhaw fry'd, or bak'd, (void of raw bits)</l>
               <l>A roſted Mallard, brace of Partridges;</l>
               <l>A Chicken-pye to march along with theſe.</l>
               <l>A brace of Woodcocks, a couple of Teals;</l>
               <l>A cold bak'd Meat, a diſh of Plovers, Quails;</l>
               <l>A diſh of Snipes, a cold bak'd Meat; thereby</l>
               <l>A diſh of Larks, a Quince, or Warden pye.</l>
               <l>A dry'd Neats tongue, an Oyſter-pye; then on</l>
               <l>A diſh of Puffs, a Joul of Sturgion.</l>
               <l>A fair laid Tart of Puff-paſte, and ſweet ſucket,</l>
               <l>A diſh of pickled Oyſters (Cloves beſtucked.)</l>
               <l>In Ord'ring of theſe Diſhes I'm ſo hoarſe,</l>
               <l>I've not ſtrength to name the look'd for third Courſe.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Apologie.</head>
               <l>I know not how you relliſh theſe my Diſhes,</l>
               <l>Nor if you daign acceptance of my Wiſhes.</l>
               <l>Some judg them like <hi>Apelles</hi> fruit, and ſome</l>
               <l>To ſuch, as ſoon as to your Feaſt would come.</l>
               <l>So we're Feaſt-hainers; th'difference is here,</l>
               <l>You feed the Mouth, and I doe feed the Ear.</l>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:104586:12"/>
            <head>Epigrams and Epitaphs.</head>
            <lg>
               <head>I. Cheater.</head>
               <l>HAſt thou, Cheater, of gold ſuch quenchleſs thirſt?</l>
               <l>I would 'twere melted, then drink while thou burſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>II. Hold-Cook.</head>
               <l>Cornutus was Cornutus call'd by's wife;</l>
               <l>And was there not great cauſe of flaming ſtrife?</l>
               <l>She thought to ſhame her Man. Alas! poor heart,</l>
               <l>I fear i'th' world to come ſhe'll have the ſmart.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>III. The Rule.</head>
               <l>'Tis good to ſpeak no ill of other men,</l>
               <l>And of our ſelves to ſpeak no good agen.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>IV. The Spice.</head>
               <l>All Vices have their taſte from Avarice;</l>
               <l>So is it one, though a corrupting, Spice.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>V. The Serpent.</head>
               <l>Sigiſmund's Stork a flatt'rer light upon,</l>
               <l>Becauſe he bit worſe then a Scorpion.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>VI. But marrs.</head>
               <l>In Dutch, But Maer is; from 't I clearly ſpy</l>
               <l>That our word Mar proceeded lineally:</l>
               <l>For we ſay ſuch an one's honeſt and wiſe,</l>
               <l>But he is greatly given unto lyes.</l>
               <l>Wherefore judge all men, you both neer and far,</l>
               <l>If But, ſo uſed, don't the Sentence marr.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>VII. Imbarbus.</head>
               <l>The Author thoſe that flout him thus doth hit;</l>
               <l>He wiſh to have never more Beard then Wit.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>VIII. Imperfect.</head>
               <l>Sure there's a myſtery in Religion lurks;</l>
               <l>Papiſts want Faith, and Proteſtants Good works.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>IX. Tautologie.</head>
               <l>I know not if 'tis queſtion, or command,</l>
               <l>In theſe words, hear, conceive, and underſtand.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>X. Epitaph on M. S.</head>
               <l>Behold a wonder! here lies ſlain<note place="margin">Anag.</note>
               </l>
               <l>One in three hours that roſe again.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>XI. Epit. on S. B.</head>
               <l>Here lies a Squire, yet ſcarce a Gentleman;</l>
               <l>A member onely of the Pinte and Can.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>XII. Epit. on Al. Camock.</head>
               <l>Here lies an Elder, Merchant, Poet, Artiſt,</l>
               <l>Who having rul'd, traded, writ, wrought, 's diſmiſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:104586:13"/>
               <head>XIII. Epit. on M. Good-rich.</head>
               <l>Here lieth one, whoſe name doth ſpeak him even</l>
               <l>On Earth accepted, and belov'd in Heaven.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>XIV. Epitaph on the late K.</head>
               <l>Zeal, Learning, Patience, Valour here doth lie,</l>
               <l>Superlative, ev'n unto ecſtaſie;</l>
               <l>That ſteer'd a State War-toſt, not by Self-will:</l>
               <l>Blame then the Storm, not th'Pilot's want of skill.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>XV. The Tranſlator.</head>
               <l>Thou ſecond Sidney, if what's laid is true,</l>
               <l>That thou tranſlat'ſt old Engliſh into new:</l>
               <l>Nay it is ſaid, that thou doſt him tranſcend;</l>
               <l>For thou amendeſt All with thy good End.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <head>To Sir <hi>R. S.</hi> Epiſtle.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>SIr, after my vow'd ſervice's remembrance,</l>
               <l>I will betray my bolder Ignorance,</l>
               <l>In letting my Muſe take another flight;</l>
               <l>Then let her on your nobler hand alight.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Whenas not great, yet good Roger à Gaunt</l>
               <l>Your kinde acceptance of my Muſe did plant</l>
               <l>Within my head, my head moſt thankful ſtill,</l>
               <l>Iſſu'd an Order to my baſer quill,</l>
               <l>My quill in hand (unjuſt) I bite my nails,</l>
               <l>Becauſe my head in brave invention fails.</l>
               <l>I would ſay ſomething, but I know not what,</l>
               <l>My Muſe is so beflagged, dull, and flat.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Yet now ſuppoſe me (dear Sir) in your preſence,</l>
               <l>Filling your ears with eloquent non-ſence,</l>
               <l>Inviting you, not, as I was your gueſt,</l>
               <l>But, as a Trav'ler, to th'Star in the Eaſt,</l>
               <l>Where, to ſpeak without pure, fantaſtick flams,</l>
               <l>Your choiceſt diſh ſhall be of Epigrams;</l>
               <l>And they perhaps to you may ſeem leſs vain</l>
               <l>Then the ſtrange diſhes of wilde France or Spain:</l>
               <l>For if I ſhould make preparations thus,</l>
               <l>You'll take me to be Heliogabalus:</l>
               <l>And now I think on't, I might ſave my prate;</l>
               <l>For you was here, I think, too long of late:</l>
               <l>And if I ſhould ſpeak out, and ſpeak it flatly,</l>
               <l>You were too lately here, it were no flatly.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Then may I to your houſe invite my ſelf,</l>
               <l>O bold, advent'rous, and audacious elf,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:104586:13"/>Shall I re-enter then your Houſes door?</l>
               <l>I ſhall be then unmannerly to Snore,</l>
               <l>And goe to Downham, ere I take my horſe,</l>
               <l>Or take my feet, and that you'll ſay is worſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>There's inconvenience in their full-crown'd—<hi>glaſſes;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>For they'll take letters out, and put in—<hi>laſſes;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Nay they'll take wit out, and of men make—<hi>aſſes:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Clipping true Engliſh comes from ful-fill'd—<hi>bowles,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Blindneſs at noon-day, as the weak-ey'd—<hi>owles.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>I like not learned Horace's thrice three,</l>
               <l>Although they of th'uneven Muſes bee,</l>
               <l>To raviſh'd high-flown Poets hieroglyphicks,</l>
               <l>Methinks they bite ſharper then keen Jambicks;</l>
               <l>Nor that ſtrange imitation of the Graces,</l>
               <l>(Although but three) which gives mens wits ſhort races;</l>
               <l>But rather like that compoſition fine,</l>
               <l>Ear-tickling wit unto heart-chearing wine;</l>
               <l>And ſith you uſe both, I would viſit you,</l>
               <l>But have no Beucephal to mount I vow:</l>
               <l>Wherefore Ile this propoſe, if t'int too courſe,</l>
               <l>Ile for a limbed change a winged horſe.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <head>
               <hi>A SONG,</hi> Made at my laſt coming out of Germany.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>WE are Neptunian boyes that come</l>
               <l>For to ſee fair Albion's ſhore,</l>
               <l>We wiſh, we wiſh to ſee our home,</l>
               <l>And to leave the brutiſh bore.</l>
               <l>Then now let our ſails be ſpred, be ſpred,</l>
               <l>Then now let our ſails be ſpred,</l>
               <l>The curled billows let us plow,</l>
               <l>And Neptunes watry bed.</l>
               <l>Jove give us a fair wind,</l>
               <l>Our Ark heels as an hind,</l>
               <l>That we ſtay not behind.</l>
               <l>Oh Jove South-eaſt,</l>
               <l>Or elſ North-eaſt,</l>
               <l>Or ſweet Eaſt!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Neptune, grant Triton t'uſher us</l>
               <l>With his auſpicious ſound;</l>
               <l>'Tis muſick not ſuperfluous;</l>
               <l>But pleaſures there abound.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:104586:14"/>If that the Monſter ſetteth ſail</l>
               <l>Vnto that joyful noiſe,</l>
               <l>Who is not moved with a gale,</l>
               <l>But then doth feel his joys</l>
               <l>He that with's mouth doth drink up Seas,</l>
               <l>And eat up floating flocks;</l>
               <l>He that the graſſie Iſlands fleas,</l>
               <l>And ſhakes the firmeſt rocks.</l>
               <l>Oh let us his ſtrength ſee,</l>
               <l>Objects let us not be;</l>
               <l>In him ſhall we ſee thee.</l>
               <l>Our mouthes up raiſe,</l>
               <l>With louder praiſe,</l>
               <l>With ſhrillerlays!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The fiercer Sea-horſe, that fell fiſh,</l>
               <l>Whoſe tooth ſo fair ſharp is,</l>
               <l>The Mare-man, merry Mare-maid fiſh,</l>
               <l>Whoſe ditty pleaſant is;</l>
               <l>That fiſh ſo muſical, and kinde</l>
               <l>Unto the ſons of men;</l>
               <l>The Dolphin brave, whoſe ſweeter minde</l>
               <l>Sav'd Orion with her fin.</l>
               <l>The wily Seal that land's,</l>
               <l>And defends her with ſands,</l>
               <l>Who has watch in her bands:</l>
               <l>The ſnorting Porpus,</l>
               <l>Husband to th' Sea-ſus;</l>
               <l>Thus, thus, thus!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The ſummer Mackril, and the Herring,</l>
               <l>That ſwim in ſuch great flocks;</l>
               <l>The wide-mouth'd Sharb who is ſo learing,</l>
               <l>The Dog the fiſhers pox.</l>
               <l>The flail-fin'd Threſher, and Sword-fiſh,</l>
               <l>The muddy Eel and Lamprel;</l>
               <l>The harmleſs Whiting which men wiſh,</l>
               <l>And the Sea-wolf ſo fell:</l>
               <l>The Fountain-fiſh that ſpouts,</l>
               <l>The Flying fiſh that ſcouts,</l>
               <l>The Load-fiſh that ſo pouts.</l>
               <l>Great Jove, we ſtand</l>
               <l>Within thy hand,</l>
               <l>Now wiſh Land.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:104586:14"/>
            <head>
               <hi>14</hi> Junii, <hi>1649.</hi> Epithalamium to M. <hi>G. Heather,</hi> who that day married Miſtreſs <hi>J. Revet.</hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <l>WHat mean the clamorous bells? the Juvenal fry?</l>
               <l>The Virgin-Troop, that march ſo amorouſly</l>
               <l>To th'place of Rendevouz? The mounting bells</l>
               <l>Are loud-mouth'd Drums, and Trumpets that excells,</l>
               <l>Beating a Call unto god Cupid's wars:</l>
               <l>But oh! who don't delight in ſuch ſweet jars?</l>
               <l>Cupid leads on the frisking Cavalry;</l>
               <l>The pleaſant Amazons march orderly</l>
               <l>Under Latona's banner; and Mars brings</l>
               <l>Some Officers to order flanks and wings.</l>
               <l>Alas! 'twas needleſs to bring Vulcan He'ther;</l>
               <l>For Nature learns to Revet well together.</l>
               <l>Their colours white, and they ſhew innocence;</l>
               <l>Yet ceaſe not this your fight, oh! in-no-ſence.</l>
               <l>Here is no danger; bravely ſound the charge;</l>
               <l>Bring up your canon, and ſtoutly diſcharge:</l>
               <l>Yet how was my brain het with ſuch fond fuel?</l>
               <l>It is no Battel, but a ſingle Duel;</l>
               <l>And ſeconds may be in a-green-way then;</l>
               <l>But pray ſtay Gallants while your time come, when</l>
               <l>Ye may go fight too; in the interim</l>
               <l>Go bite your handkerchiefs, and think on them.</l>
               <l>Come, Bridegroom, let me whiſper in your ear;</l>
               <l>Coun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>el is good to all that will it hear;</l>
               <l>Lavolta's you muſt dance; and mounting then,</l>
               <l>Your Bride will dance all th' dances o'er agen.</l>
               <l>Muſick, pray ceaſe; for I dare lay a ſhilling</l>
               <l>The ſenſe of Hearing is not like the Feeling.</l>
               <l>Vncivil gueſts, be gone, and bid good-night,</l>
               <l>Or elſe if I come, I'll put out the light.</l>
               <l>Ye ſenſleſs animals to talk of noon;</l>
               <l>What if they did? I ſay 'twas not too ſoon.</l>
               <l>Come, leave your tatling, goſſips, and be gone;</l>
               <l>Ye make the Bride bluſh like a roſe in June.</l>
               <l>Bluſh not (ſweet Bride.) Go, Hymen, light your torch,</l>
               <l>And uſher out theſe gueſts out of the porch:</l>
               <l>For if the proudeſt of you dare to tarry,</l>
               <l>I'll ſcourge you with a ſmart make-Satyr, marry.</l>
               <l>And for theſe lingring Virgins, oh, Prieſt, lo,</l>
               <l>If you'ld but marry them, then they would go.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:104586:15"/>
            <head>The PRAYER.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>FAir Bride, may ev'ry night you go to bed</l>
               <l>Give your good Husband a new Maiden-head,</l>
               <l>And if he chance to ever think amiſſe,</l>
               <l>May your ſweet lips then charm him with a kiſs.</l>
               <l>Then that the World may ſee yon are no ſtarters,</l>
               <l>May a ſon bleſs you at lawfull three quarters!</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <div type="part">
               <head>A Farewell to the World. Satyr <hi>1. OR</hi> A Comment on a Copy of Verſes.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>"FArewell, ye honour'd raggs, ye Chriſtal bubbles;</l>
                  <l>"Farewell, ye lying joyes, ye pleaſing troubles.</l>
                  <l>Wiſe Salomon ſaith, Earth's moſt choice things merit</l>
                  <l>Is vanity, with vexing of the ſpirit.</l>
                  <l>Theſe raggs are worn, theſe chriſtall bubbles choking,</l>
                  <l>Theſe joyes are lies, theſe pleaſing troubles croking.</l>
                  <l>Therefore, vain World, of thee I take farewell,</l>
                  <l>Before I reaſons fully to thee tell.</l>
                  <l>"Fame's but an hollow Eccho, gold pure clay,</l>
                  <l>"Honour the darling but of one ſhort day.</l>
                  <l>Fame's a muſhrum, which Pliny doth repute</l>
                  <l>Nature's chiefe miracle having no root:</l>
                  <l>E le had thoſe Grecians, and thoſe Romans brave</l>
                  <l>For their atchievements never found a Grave;</l>
                  <l>And beſides where ſhall empty Fame be hurl'd</l>
                  <l>When God doth make a bone-fire of the world?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Great ſtore of Gold can not be gotten in,</l>
                  <l>And kept (ſaith learn'd Eraſmus) without ſin.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And that deceitfull, though moſt glorious clay,</l>
                  <l>Behold! maketh it wings, and flies away.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Ah! how was Julius Caeſar s honour lay'd</l>
                  <l>In blood? And how moſt ſtrangely wa'ſt betray'd?</l>
                  <l>How faild great Pompey's ſtate? whoſe ſtory ſad</l>
                  <l>Would make a man in honour halfe grow mad?</l>
                  <l>How were thoſe wretched Kings, that for the riot</l>
                  <l>Of their proud foe, did draw his Chariot?</l>
                  <l>How was it with that poor dejected King,</l>
                  <l>His vile depoſing by foes ſuffering?</l>
                  <l>How was it with one of the Royall blood,</l>
                  <l>The neereſt heire, ah! who not only ſtood</l>
                  <l>Barehead, but barefoot ran, oh cruelty!</l>
                  <l>After the train of mounted Burgundy.</l>
                  <l>Stanly preſuming of his ſurer hold,</l>
                  <l>Was'nt onely unexpectedly controld,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="11" facs="tcp:104586:15"/>But at no warning, oh the viler deed!</l>
                  <l>By crooked Richard ſhortned by the head.</l>
                  <l>Fame hath no root, gold tried is but droſs,</l>
                  <l>And by that vaunting honour is moſt loſs.</l>
                  <l>"Beauty's chief Idol's but a damask skin,</l>
                  <l>"State but a golden priſon to keep in,</l>
                  <l>"And torture free-born minds; imbroid'red trains</l>
                  <l>"Are but the iſſues of fantaſtick braines.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>A daſh of natur's tincture laid upon</l>
                  <l>The skin, by ſickneſs waſhed of anon,</l>
                  <l>Is beauty. And what but a fair bloſſom,</l>
                  <l>That drops, as fruit offer's thereon to come?</l>
                  <l>What but a flower, oh ye fondling mortals!</l>
                  <l>Which with one hot Sun-beam wealtreth, and falls?</l>
                  <l>He that did with a thouſand beauties ly,</l>
                  <l>Said favour is deceit, beauty vanity.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>State ſtill ingendreth Envy, and we ſee,</l>
                  <l>Each hath a cudgell for a laden Tree.</l>
                  <l>All th' cures 'ith Street in fierce purſuit are gone</l>
                  <l>Of that poor cur that runneth with the bone.</l>
                  <l>How many even in this age of ours,</l>
                  <l>Whom wealth betray'd, and made malefactors?</l>
                  <l>One ſaith, State is n't only a priſon foul;</l>
                  <l>But doth avouch it the bane of the ſoul.</l>
                  <l>How fearfull are the great to tread awry,</l>
                  <l>Becauſe they're watched by many a ſpie?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Imbroid'red traines, what are they? ev'n the beſt</l>
                  <l>Are borrowed from ſome ſtranger bird, or beaſt;</l>
                  <l>And all attires. The Bever ownes the Hat.</l>
                  <l>As for th' ſilk-ſtocking, the ſilk-worm owneth that.</l>
                  <l>The Sheep the Suit and Cloak. The Boot &amp; Shoe the Neat,</l>
                  <l>And if this ſtrip'd the Gallant ſcarce would ſweat,</l>
                  <l>Beauty's a paint detected, States a Cage</l>
                  <l>Of Iron, Traines a folly in young age.</l>
                  <l>"And blood ally'd to greatneſſe is but loan</l>
                  <l>"Inherited, not purchas'd, not her own.</l>
                  <l>What thy Father by his worth deſerved</l>
                  <l>Belongs not to thee, nor for thee reſerved;</l>
                  <l>Saith one (and be it known he was no bable)</l>
                  <l>It is thine own deſerts muſt make thee noble;</l>
                  <l>For that which by our Anceſtors is ſown,</l>
                  <l>Becauſe not ours, is ſcarcely call'd our own;</l>
                  <l>Greatneſs of blood without claiming deſert,</l>
                  <l>By wiſe men is not valew'd worth a fart.</l>
                  <l>"Fame, Riches, Hoonur, Beauty, State, Trains, Birth,</l>
                  <l>"Are but the fading pleaſures of the Earth.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="12" facs="tcp:104586:16"/>Adde, if you pleaſe, ſtrength, valour, pleaſure, wiſdom;</l>
                  <l>Corruption all theſe doth overcome.</l>
                  <l>"I would be high, but ſee the Sun doth ſtill</l>
                  <l>"Level his beams againſt the riſing hill.</l>
                  <l>I ſee the common humour doth abet</l>
                  <l>The ax to be i'th' blood of Nobles wet.</l>
                  <l>LAUD and STRAFFORD had n't had ſo ill a fate,</l>
                  <l>But that they mounted were in Church and State.</l>
                  <l>Therefore advance I wiſh not in extremes,</l>
                  <l>For fear the Sun ſhould melt it with his beams.</l>
                  <l>"I would be rich, but ſee man too unkinde,</l>
                  <l>"Digging the bowels of the richeſt mine.</l>
                  <l>And therefore is it that it ſeemeth reaſon</l>
                  <l>To make rich men guilty of high Treaſon.</l>
                  <l>Oh how men pine when a fair houſe is ſhown,</l>
                  <l>That (they think) a too wealthy man doth own!</l>
                  <l>"I would be wiſe, but that the Fox I ſee</l>
                  <l>"Suſpected guilty, whilſt the Aſs goes free.</l>
                  <l>Oh the great ſafety of a Fool! the Gull</l>
                  <l>(A bird much found among the Worſhipful)</l>
                  <l>Danger afflicts not: but the Nightingale</l>
                  <l>The thorns her breſt prick, and ſhe it doth wail.</l>
                  <l>The Flail and Sword-fiſh do not finde a fault</l>
                  <l>With ſilly quiet fiſh, but th' Whale aſſault.</l>
                  <l>Therefore but note the myſtery of it;</l>
                  <l>Wiſe men cut off, Fools ſav'd for want of wit.</l>
                  <l>"I would be poor, but ſee the humble graſs</l>
                  <l>"Trampled upon by each unworthy aſs.</l>
                  <l>As that Souldier leaping ſhort o' th' ditch,</l>
                  <l>The Company (each one) made him their bridge:</l>
                  <l>Yet none but Aſſes to the humble can</l>
                  <l>Forget ſo much the other is a man.</l>
                  <l>"Wiſe ſuſpected, High envi'd more,</l>
                  <l>"Rich hated, Fair tempted, ſcorn'd if Poor.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>"Would the world now adopt me for her heir,</l>
                  <l>"And Beauty's queen entitle me The fair:</l>
                  <l>Were I as famous ev'n as Hercules,</l>
                  <l>With Croeſus riches, and of both the Indies,</l>
                  <l>And as much honour as an Alexander,</l>
                  <l>Walking with Venus in loves ſweet Maeander,</l>
                  <l>And as much ſtate as (ſometime) Solomon,</l>
                  <l>As rich attire as Cleopatra on</l>
                  <l>My back, with neer alliance unto Kings;</l>
                  <l>Lord, what are theſe but flatt'ring fading things!</l>
                  <l>Were I the moſt Angelick creature living,</l>
                  <l>Who, though a widower, need not go a wiving:</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="13" facs="tcp:104586:16"/>"Could I vye Angels with rich Indian meads,</l>
                  <l>"Or with a ſpeaking eye command bare heads.</l>
                  <l>Had I all Vſurer's baggs in mine own keeping;</l>
                  <l>(But they, nor I, could not then reſt by ſleeping)</l>
                  <l>Or could my nobler eye ſpeak Majeſty,</l>
                  <l>And make men humbly at my feet to lie.</l>
                  <l>"Could I be more then any man that live's,</l>
                  <l>"Fair, rich, great, all in ſuperlatives.</l>
                  <l>Were I more, then can be, moſt fair, moſt rich,</l>
                  <l>Moſt wiſe, moſt great, t'would be a lying itch,</l>
                  <l>Which ſeem's to tickle at the firſt; but lo!</l>
                  <l>It make's a man into halfe frenzy go.</l>
                  <l>"I count one minute of my holy leiſure</l>
                  <l>"Beyond too much of all this worldly pleaſure.</l>
                  <l>One ſpirituall ejaculation</l>
                  <l>Is better then to rule a mighty Nation.</l>
                  <l>How ſweet is it, for to converſe with God,</l>
                  <l>Holding his Scepter out inſtead of Rod!</l>
                  <l>With Paul to be in the third Heavens rapt,</l>
                  <l>Which for to be, each humbled foule is apt.</l>
                  <l>"A Book of Prayers ſhall be my lookinglaſs,</l>
                  <l>"Wherein I'll ſee, and court ſweet Vertue's face.</l>
                  <l>In Prayer I will ſee God's face; vertue</l>
                  <l>By Heathens call'd is now Religion true.</l>
                  <l>Shunning of vice, and loving that is good,</l>
                  <l>Now virtue's beauteous face hath loſt her hood.</l>
                  <l>"Here will I ſit, and ſigh my hot youth's folly,</l>
                  <l>"And learn t'affect an holy melancholly.</l>
                  <l>Ah! here I'll grieve for with ſad ſighs, and grones,</l>
                  <l>Sins by my marrow-hot-inflamed bones.</l>
                  <l>My ſins of youth with David I'll lament,</l>
                  <l>'Till God doth ſay thou do'ſt, and I'll repent.</l>
                  <l>"And if contentment be a ſtranger then,</l>
                  <l>"I'll never look for't, but in Heav'n age'n.</l>
                  <l>'Twas that made Iſrael ſafe in the red Sea,</l>
                  <l>The bleſt three Children in the fire to be</l>
                  <l>Vnſcorched, and David to fight Goliah,</l>
                  <l>And Jeſus earthly Mother bleſt Maria</l>
                  <l>Scape Herod's cruelty. Joſeph i'th pit,</l>
                  <l>And in the Priſon ſo for to imbrace it.</l>
                  <l>Stephen amid a ſhower of ſtones to ſtand</l>
                  <l>Thrice bleſt, holding of Chriſt by heart, and hand.</l>
                  <l>Note 'twas contentment under God's great hand,</l>
                  <l>That made them waighting for deliverance ſtand.</l>
                  <l>If then contentment be'nt in faith to God,</l>
                  <l>Contentment by me is not underſtood.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:104586:17"/>
               <head>D. Rogero Sotheby Mercatori, ut pignus obſervantia D.D.D. hunc Papam-Daemon. N.M. Satyr. <hi>2.</hi> The PICTVRE.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <l>Haec pictura videt monachum nunc eſſe per omnes;</l>
                     <l>Sed modo verte parùm, Daemon ut ipſe videt.</l>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <lg>
                  <l>RUn, run, run, run: what are you mad to ſtay?</l>
                  <l>Sluggard, there is no Lion in the way,</l>
                  <l>To ſtop thy flight from a more monſtrous beaſt</l>
                  <l>Then the ſtrange formed Creatures of the Eaſt.</l>
                  <l>Thou piece of lying holineſs avaunt,</l>
                  <l>Thou gold-devouring, gaping Cormorant,</l>
                  <l>Thou beaſt with ſeaven hornes, heathen in heart,</l>
                  <l>Although thou haſt of lies guilding the Art.</l>
                  <l>Thou Tyber-Tyger, thirſting after blood</l>
                  <l>Of ſuch as thou wilt never be ſo good;</l>
                  <l>Methinks that thoſe that come to kiſs thy Toe,</l>
                  <l>Should let their eyes a little further go,</l>
                  <l>And there ſee with an halfe eye, and halfe blind,</l>
                  <l>How foul he's under his vizard behind:</l>
                  <l>His Tripple Crown declares that triple evill,</l>
                  <l>Of failing fleſh, baſe world, and curſed Devill;</l>
                  <l>Nay throw him down from off his Papall-ſeat,</l>
                  <l>And he uncaſed then will make you ſweat.</l>
                  <l>Look one way here, and then a Pope you ſee,</l>
                  <l>And but reverſ't the Devill a Pope is he,</l>
                  <l>A two horn'd Devill, and there is no hope</l>
                  <l>That he can e're returne again to Pope.</l>
                  <l>But take him at the beſt he is ſo evill,</l>
                  <l>That I muſt ſtyle him here a right Pope-Devill,</l>
                  <l>Or Devill-Pope, which is not my meer humour,</l>
                  <l>Or taking up on truſt of lying rumour;</l>
                  <l>But as the Devil proud was, ſo is he,</l>
                  <l>And as it was his ruine, 'twill his be.</l>
                  <l>The Devill we know all was ſuch a lyar,</l>
                  <l>That he deceiv'd our Grandam Eve's deſire,</l>
                  <l>And promiſed to give Man-God the Orb,</l>
                  <l>Whenas he need not his heart ſo diſturb;</l>
                  <l>For it was none of his to give; ſo th' Pope</l>
                  <l>Blaſphemouſly doth give to ſinners ſcope</l>
                  <l>To ſwim in ſins, and this it is deceives,</l>
                  <l>He ſayth his pardon puniſhment reprieves,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="15" facs="tcp:104586:17"/>And ſaith he cannot erre, oh errour great,</l>
                  <l>Crept unto ſuch a learn'd abuſed ſeat.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Simil.</hi> Thus have I ſeen a picture that one way</l>
                  <l>Was man, th'other a womans face diſplay.</l>
                  <l>So have I heard of Crocodiles deceit,</l>
                  <l>Diſſembling Childrens cries have layd a bait.</l>
                  <l>So have I ſeen an apple good to th' eye,</l>
                  <l>To th' better proving mouth hath giv'n the lye.</l>
                  <l>So have I known a braſſe ring gilt all over,</l>
                  <l>Which trying time the falſity diſcover.</l>
                  <l>Such Pictures, Crocodiles, Apples, and Rings,</l>
                  <l>May with the Pope be call'd deceitfull things.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The Map of vice: Italian Atheiſme,</l>
                  <l>Spains pride, French lightneſs, and their Schiſme,</l>
                  <l>Dutch drunkeneſſe, Jews ſuperſtition,</l>
                  <l>And ſuch that if I would make inquiſition,</l>
                  <l>I could compare him I dare here proteſt</l>
                  <l>To no one man; but to Lucifer beſt.</l>
                  <l>Manfroy's ambition commeth ſhort of his;</l>
                  <l>Ravillacks murther that, then his was leſs.</l>
                  <l>Nero's vile cruelty he doth out do,</l>
                  <l>And Paris theft like his is nothing ſo;</l>
                  <l>More Tyrant then Caligula; more vile</l>
                  <l>And wav'ring then the Emperour of Nile</l>
                  <l>Was to Gods choſen Iſrael; reaſon</l>
                  <l>Will ſay he hath out-done Sylla's vile treaſon.</l>
                  <l>'Tis true he's like Caligula in this</l>
                  <l>He doth repine at all mens happineſs.</l>
                  <l>Cleopatra, and Semiramis luſts</l>
                  <l>To his great ſtormes, are but as ſmaller gifts.</l>
                  <l>Proud Diocleſian that call'd the Sun</l>
                  <l>Brother, comes behind him, for he don't ſhun</l>
                  <l>T'uſurp Chriſts place to be head of the Church;</l>
                  <l>For curſed Avarice he is as much</l>
                  <l>Guilty as baſe Hermocrates, who did</l>
                  <l>Bequeath his goods unto himſelfe when dead.</l>
                  <l>The Sabies were not ſo idle as he,</l>
                  <l>Nor do I think that any man can be.</l>
                  <l>The Tyrant Dionyſius by drink</l>
                  <l>That loſt his eyes, was not his match I think.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Wherefore I pardon crave to have begun,</l>
                  <l>That which by betters muſt be over-don,</l>
                  <l>Sith I come ſhort in all things; but I hope,</l>
                  <l>Some will from this more underſtand the Pope,</l>
                  <l>And at my younger hands take it not evill,</l>
                  <l>Sith I do juſtly ſtile him a Pope-Devill.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="16" facs="tcp:104586:18"/>Duitz is te ſpraek met via'ndts, (ſoo ſegg'ſy) maer,</l>
                  <l>As met een via'ndt wy ſpraek, wy foudt bewaer;</l>
                  <l>J'ck can niet ſwart whit ſegg'; ſoo van de Paep,</l>
                  <l>Jck can niet ſegg' hy opſta'et, as hy ſlaep.</l>
                  <l>De Jude will niet dat Chriſtus hier heeft' weſt,</l>
                  <l>De Pauſt dat hy ſoudt regulere; de beſt'</l>
                  <l>Wy weet elk ſoek ſijn ſelve; oh lieve Heere!</l>
                  <l>Coninck van konincks du muſt reguleere,</l>
                  <l>En de hovaerdich monnick ſeggen wy</l>
                  <l>Muſt weer weſen <hi>Servus Servorum Dei.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Drunkeneſſe Satyr. 3.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>VVHen I thus ruminate, oh Heav'ns me bleſs!</l>
                  <l>The Apiſh tricks of wilder Drunkenneſs.</l>
                  <l>Thoſe thirty Tyrants in that Heathen State</l>
                  <l>More dire, unheard of things did ne'r create,</l>
                  <l>Then theſe mad thirty Sons of Drunkeneſs,</l>
                  <l>Some ſeeming vertues; yet moſt horrid vices.</l>
                  <l>Oh wonder! here the miracle ſtill lies,</l>
                  <l>It doth delight it ſelfe in contraries.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Witty, Fooliſh, waking, ſleepy, angry,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Pleaſant, faith-full-leſſe, valiant, cowardly,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Quarrelſom, loving, healthfull, ſick, then come</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Covetous, liberall, ſpeaking and dumb,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Lame, walking, ſecret, open, lecherous, chaſt,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Care-full-leſſe, proud, humble, mad quiet's laſt.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="1">
                  <head>1.</head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Witty,</hi> or empty boldnſſe for conceit,</l>
                  <l>Is ſubject to be cheated by deceit.</l>
                  <l>How have I heard a vafering blade diſpence</l>
                  <l>With a conceited wit; but meer non-ſence?</l>
                  <l>How have I heard a thunder thumping wit</l>
                  <l>Sometimes his friend, ſometimes himſelfe to hit?</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Sim</hi> So have I ſeen a glitt'ring weapon ſtand</l>
                  <l>In a mad man's ill-regulated hand.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="2">
                  <head>2.</head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Fooliſh,</hi> for motly Drunkards ſlaver, yaun,</l>
                  <l>As it they were a witleſs changelings ſpaun,</l>
                  <l>Wanting the utterance of words, drawing</l>
                  <l>To void his Vrine, like beaſts, his Cud chawing.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Sim.</hi> So have I ſeen, an Ideot in the ſtreet,</l>
                  <l>Shewing his ware to all that do him meet.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="3">
                  <head>3.</head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Waking,</hi> when he hath far more need of ſleep</l>
                  <l>Againſt it do his ſences cent'ry keep,</l>
                  <l>His eyes ſpeak want; yet do's his pride ſay no,</l>
                  <l>He ſay's he's ſober when he's nothing ſo.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="17" facs="tcp:104586:18"/>
                     <hi>Sim.</hi> So have I ſeen expences that were large,</l>
                  <l>When he could not defray one hafe o'th charge.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="4">
                  <head>4.</head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Sleepy,</hi> that friends can't raiſe him to a bed,</l>
                  <l>Heavy with Drunkennes, as duller lead.</l>
                  <l>The noiſe of dreadfull thunder, nor of waves</l>
                  <l>That Lion-like do roar, nor he that raves</l>
                  <l>Tormented by Perillus bull, or winds</l>
                  <l>Impetuous rage this man ſtill ſleeping find's.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Sim.</hi> So do Chirurgions their Patients keep</l>
                  <l>From ſence of pain by a benumming ſleep.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="5">
                  <head>5.</head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Angry,</hi> ſtill finding fault, and ever thinking</l>
                  <l>That he is jeer'd, never content (but drinking)</l>
                  <l>Oh! he ha's no reſpect, not worthy he</l>
                  <l>(And there he's right) of the good Company.</l>
                  <l>His eyes red, glaring, rouling, ſparkling ſo,</l>
                  <l>A, if he would devoure thoſe that ſay no</l>
                  <l>To his affirmed lyes: in his ſhort madneſs.</l>
                  <l>Now are his cheeks become as pale as aſhes,</l>
                  <l>Then fiery, and ſwoln up, as with poiſon.</l>
                  <l>His quivring head and hands ſhaking upon</l>
                  <l>His ſenceleſſe Trunk, and his Lips quivering,</l>
                  <l>His foul mouth foming, and his tongue doubling,</l>
                  <l>His reeling feet unconſtantly ſhifting,</l>
                  <l>And his full-gorged ſtomack alwayes lifting,</l>
                  <l>And the whole man wholly unlike himſelfe,</l>
                  <l>So furious is this our ridiculous elſe.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Sim.</hi> So have I ſeen a Curr to bite the ſtones</l>
                  <l>Thrown at him whereby he breakes his jaw-bones.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="6">
                  <head>6.</head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Pleaſant,</hi> he ſpeak's as one learning the Sauter,</l>
                  <l>Mopping and mowing he ingend'reth laughter</l>
                  <l>By much of which a foole is known: how merry</l>
                  <l>Is he become by drinking ſearching ſherry?</l>
                  <l>Dancing Corranto's, and fine Northren Jiggs,</l>
                  <l>Vnmercifully thumping wentches giggs.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Sim.</hi> So here's the difference of this frollick wherry</l>
                  <l>Others are mad fools; but this is the merry.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="7">
                  <head>7.</head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Quarelſome,</hi> as thoſe that do whore and drab,</l>
                  <l>Or Alexander who did Clitus ſtab.</l>
                  <l>So that Tyrant Cambiſes be'ng reprov'd</l>
                  <l>For Drunkeneſs ſhot his Son much belov'd,</l>
                  <l>And ſay'd unnat'rall Father, whoſe words ſtunk,</l>
                  <l>See what a ſteady hand I've now I'm Drunk.</l>
                  <l>And ſome men then commonly give the Glove</l>
                  <l>For deſp'rate Duells where they, had firm love.</l>
                  <l>Some men (ſome what more harmleſs) for they'll cuſſe</l>
                  <l>On no occaſion giving counter buſſe.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="18" facs="tcp:104586:19"/>
                     <hi>Sim.</hi> So have I heard men (if I don't miſtake them,)</l>
                  <l>That know mens words better then they that ſpeak them.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="8">
                  <head>8.</head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Loving</hi> ſo fervently his drunken mate,</l>
                  <l>That you would think there was no place for hate,</l>
                  <l>Vowing he'll lend him hundreds, when alas!</l>
                  <l>The borrower (God know's) his own caſe was.</l>
                  <l>He love's, he love's, he love's with ſo great vigour,</l>
                  <l>As you can ſcarce believe, (but 'tis the liquour)</l>
                  <l>And he beginneth friendſhip with another,</l>
                  <l>Who he doth ſwear ſhall be dearer then's Brother;</l>
                  <l>But it may chance to fall e'r they do part,</l>
                  <l>That he doth give his hand in lieu of heart.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Sim.</hi> So have I ſeen two Children kiſs each other</l>
                  <l>But now, and preſently each ſtrike the other.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="9">
                  <head>9.</head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Faithfull</hi> if't may be called ſo; for ſome</l>
                  <l>Vnto his friend a ſecond will become,</l>
                  <l>And to his drunken inflam'd friend add fewell</l>
                  <l>To perpetrate a wretched dangerous duell.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Sim.</hi> So have I heard, that one did ſwear, and ſwagger</l>
                  <l>He'd kill himſelfe, and th' Devill reach'd a Dagger.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="10">
                  <head>10.</head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Faithleſſe</hi> pretending friendſhip; yet his coyn</l>
                  <l>Indeavouring by wiles for to purloyn,</l>
                  <l>And by that curſed play of Cards, and Dice</l>
                  <l>Trim up his own new clothes with nits and lice.</l>
                  <l>So doth the Crocodile weep, and yet watch</l>
                  <l>If by his wiles a prey he well can catch.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="11">
                  <head>11.</head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Valiant,</hi> he dare tell Belzebub he lies,</l>
                  <l>And in this humour Hercules defies,</l>
                  <l>Dare fight a Troup, out-dare the thundring Ordnance,</l>
                  <l>'Gainſt ev'ry man his vap'ring fiſts advance.</l>
                  <l>But when he's ſober he's another temper,</l>
                  <l>And his ſirname is Innocentius ſemper.</l>
                  <l>So have I heard one hath contemn'd the Mayor,</l>
                  <l>And the next day hath waited at his ſtayr.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="12">
                  <head>12.</head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Cowardly,</hi> and as Puſillanimous,</l>
                  <l>As with the frog was that combating mouſe</l>
                  <l>In Aeſops Fables, or thoſe famous Clownes</l>
                  <l>By Sidney plac'd in the Arcadian downes,</l>
                  <l>Each other by their Challenges ſo frighting,</l>
                  <l>That they can ſcarce refrain their britches —</l>
                  <l>Box him, and beat him, call him rogue, and raſcall;</l>
                  <l>Yet he moſt vertuouſly doth put up all.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Sim.</hi> So have I ſeen a ſtrayed our in 'th ſtreets,</l>
                  <l>Bitten by all; yet cringes t'all he meets.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="13">
                  <head>13.</head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Healthfull,</hi> ſo that his ſtomach is not ſqueſy,</l>
                  <l>Although his witt may be ſomewhat too lazy.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="19" facs="tcp:104586:19"/>
                     <hi>Sim.</hi> So have I ſeen at Sea a Sea-man young,</l>
                  <l>Not ſick, but did no work, but with his tongue.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="14">
                  <head>14.</head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Sick,</hi> that you'ld connſell him to make his Will;</l>
                  <l>But you in fine ſhan't find him halfe ſo ill.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Sim.</hi> So have I ſeen a vagrant lame in ſhow,</l>
                  <l>That if detected, was found nothing ſo.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="15">
                  <head>15.</head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Covetous</hi> in extreams, that he wont pay</l>
                  <l>His reckoning upon that ſelfe ſame day</l>
                  <l>He did with Bacchus feaſt, nor draw his coyn;</l>
                  <l>For he ſuppoſes his own hands purloyn.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Sim.</hi> So have I ſeen the ſpirits tormenting rack</l>
                  <l>Grudge at the clothes he wore upon his back.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="16">
                  <head>16.</head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Liberall,</hi> that he'll give his hat from's head,</l>
                  <l>His Britches from his britch; nay 'tis ſe'd</l>
                  <l>His palfray he'll preſent to him perchance,</l>
                  <l>Through impudence that to him did advance.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Sim.</hi> So have I ſeen a Child in a pleaſ'd vain</l>
                  <l>Give's bread and butter, and crie for't again.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="17">
                  <head>17.</head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Speaking</hi> like Marcus Tullius Cicero,</l>
                  <l>His nimble tongue in it's careers ſhall go</l>
                  <l>Of all diſcourſe a true Monopolizer,</l>
                  <l>When as (God wot) he ſcarce is thought the wiſer.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Sim.</hi> So have I heard Rooks to vociferate,</l>
                  <l>When birds far more harmonious ſtill ſate:</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="18">
                  <head>18.</head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Dumb,</hi> as was Aeſop, and a mouth as ſhut,</l>
                  <l>As he for prating whoſe Coxcomb was cut;</l>
                  <l>As mute as fiſhes are, creatures immur'd,</l>
                  <l>Or thoſe that have not wit to ſpeak a word.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Sim.</hi> So have I ſeen a Malefactors crime</l>
                  <l>Hath made him ſpeechleſs for that dreadful time</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="19">
                  <head>19.</head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Lame</hi> as the Savoy can afford, his feet</l>
                  <l>Alas! ſubject too often for to meet:</l>
                  <l>A true Noun Adjective cant ſtand alone;</l>
                  <l>But as th' Maeanders on Indentures done,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Sim.</hi> So reel his feebled feet. So have I ſeen</l>
                  <l>A man in ſickneſs that full weak hath been.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="20">
                  <head>20.</head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Walking,</hi> that by his well-trod ſteps you'd think,</l>
                  <l>Drink was'nt in him, nor was the man in drink;</l>
                  <l>So like a ſober man, and not defeated,</l>
                  <l>That wiſer men then I might wel be cheated,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Sim.</hi> So are there whores like honeſt women; ſhame!</l>
                  <l>For ev'ry like (ye know) is not the ſame.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="21">
                  <head>21.</head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Secret,</hi> he wi'nt declare what he wil do.</l>
                  <l>Ye ſhall not know when he to — does go,</l>
                  <l>Nor when he kiſſ'd that handſome woman: no;</l>
                  <l>His ſecrets in his ſecret breſt do grow.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="20" facs="tcp:104586:20"/>
                     <hi>Sim.</hi> So have I ſeen men in an high-ſtretch'd frolick</l>
                  <l>Whiſper th' eſcape of the tormenting Chollick.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="22">
                  <head>22.</head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Open,</hi> he'll tell you what purſe he did cut,</l>
                  <l>That he did lie with ſuch a dirty ſlut,</l>
                  <l>What are his reſolutions, how fine</l>
                  <l>He will be when at ſuch a place he dine.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Sim.</hi> So have I known a wench whoſe tongue did burn</l>
                  <l>In ſleep to tell who did her a good turn.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="23">
                  <head>23.</head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Leacherous,</hi> unto Whores, to girles, to boyes,</l>
                  <l>To dirty drabs, and in ſuch brutiſh wayes,</l>
                  <l>As whether it may cauſe my griefe, or mirth</l>
                  <l>I know not, but the vileſt Jade on'th Earth</l>
                  <l>Was for his turn, with, Madam, one ſalute,</l>
                  <l>Sometimes ſhe's ſtubborn, ſometimes proſtitute.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Sim.</hi> So do wee ſee the feavour crave for cold,</l>
                  <l>When it is preſent death I dare be bold.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="24">
                  <head>24.</head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Chaſt</hi> as Diana, becauſe luſt is paſt,</l>
                  <l>I therefore think it ſcarce is called chaſt.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Sim.</hi> So is occult a murtherous intent,</l>
                  <l>Becauſe his murth'rous humour hath no vent.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="25">
                  <head>25.</head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Carefull</hi> of all his friends that have exceſſe</l>
                  <l>Even unto riot by their Drunkennes.</l>
                  <l>Oh cover him ſaith he upon the bed,</l>
                  <l>Becauſe the bolder wine hath ſtorm'd his head,</l>
                  <l>Lend him your hand down thoſe two dangerous ſtairs,</l>
                  <l>Wake him betime, to think on his affairs.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Sim.</hi> So have I ſeen one that excusd'd his friend</l>
                  <l>From drinking much; yet he hath drunk his end.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="26">
                  <head>26.</head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Careleſſe,</hi> he weig's nor life, nor limb, nor gold,</l>
                  <l>Hazards his life, and limb, throw's gold untold,</l>
                  <l>And ſweares he'll pave the houſe therewith, he hates</l>
                  <l>That odious crew of ruminating pates.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Sim.</hi> So have I ſeen men maz'd at Sea, and ſtand</l>
                  <l>Expecting Death whilſt freed by 'another hand.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="27">
                  <head>27.</head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Proud,</hi> and ſo haughty, that a poor Mechanick</l>
                  <l>Shall not the drops fal'n on the Table lick,</l>
                  <l>Wonders at men's intruſions, and think's</l>
                  <l>The man much honour'd ſtill that with him drinks,</l>
                  <l>He that he cuff's, is knighted, and his ſpit</l>
                  <l>Miraculouſly doth ingender wit.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Sim</hi> So have I ſeen a man conceive applaud</l>
                  <l>From Auditors, when his conceit was fraud.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="28">
                  <head>28.</head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Humble,</hi> that he'll ſalute him, that before</l>
                  <l>He would have honour'd with a nod, not more,</l>
                  <l>Your very humble Servant, Sir: I vow,</l>
                  <l>As at the Heathen Alters ſo he'll bow</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="21" facs="tcp:104586:20"/>
                     <hi>Sim.</hi> To evr'y man. So doth the Maſt i'th'wind:</l>
                  <l>But it impetuoſity combin'd.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="29">
                  <head>29.</head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Mad,</hi> that he makes men camping-bals, he wrings</l>
                  <l>Mens arms, as Buts of wine are wrung in ſlings.</l>
                  <l>He tears the Cloaths, abuſe your fame, and thumbs,</l>
                  <l>Your faces, backs, your bellies and your bumbs.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Sim.</hi> As hardly tame doth reaſon ſuch mens ſprites,</l>
                  <l>As water, fire; or counſell Bedlamites.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="30">
                  <head>30.</head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Quiet,</hi> he th'object, you the Inſtrument,</l>
                  <l>Doe to him what your wits can e'r invent,</l>
                  <l>He is not mov'd, he is no man of paſſion;</l>
                  <l>But is, alaſs! an object of compaſſion.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Sim.</hi> So have I ſeen a mad Bull ſo bemir'd,</l>
                  <l>That his mad Frenſie now is wholly tyr'd.</l>
                  <l>In fine, all Writers, that did, doe, or ever can</l>
                  <l>Write learnedly, can ne'r define this man,</l>
                  <l>This Proteus metamorphiſed to ſhapes</l>
                  <l>Of all beaſts; but moſt like to thoſe of Apes.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Rimer routed. <hi>Satyr</hi> 4. OR, <hi>Replies to</hi> R. D. <hi>his Papers by</hi> N. de Monford. <hi>R. D. his firſt Paper.</hi>
               </head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <lg>
                        <l>A Cup of good Sack</l>
                        <l>To ſtrengthen the back,</l>
                        <l>brought home by the good Shipmaſter;</l>
                        <l>I pray you good NICK,</l>
                        <l>At this time be you quick,</l>
                        <l>You ſhall be the Poëtaſter.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <head type="sub">The Reply.</head>
               <l>OH who DOB, who— what turn'd a Poët-tarter?</l>
               <l>So have I Muſick heard from a skill'd farter;</l>
               <l>But there are accents, and your Verſe had none;</l>
               <l>And if they'd ſenſe, then were my ſenſes gone:</l>
               <l>But you will ſay 'twas Fancy. Such a look,</l>
               <l>As he that miſtook a bold tenter-hook</l>
               <l>That ſeis'd upon his Cloak, fearing a brute,</l>
               <l>And ruder Sergeant, ſaid, Sir, at whoſe ſute?</l>
               <l>In ſuch confuſed fear, I fear you writ</l>
               <l>This Sonnet, and by it think your duller wit</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:104586:21"/>Did want the thing you ſpake of, quickning ſack,</l>
               <l>Then be good fellow ROBIN, you ſha'nt lack</l>
               <l>A half pint from him, who when you do come</l>
               <l>Shall wiſh the Muſe ſpeak better, or be dumb.</l>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>R. D.</hi> Watchmaker, his ſecond Paper.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>SO goe Sir NICHLIS goe,</l>
                  <l>Your verſes like Tobias dog, ſo, ſo,</l>
                  <l>Whatſoever you ſeem to be,</l>
                  <l>There is more Poëts then we;</l>
                  <l>For tainter hooks, they are in rook-alley,</l>
                  <l>Near to the travally:</l>
                  <l>And for my Cloke, I have but one</l>
                  <l>Once paid for good deed done.</l>
                  <l>For the thing you call my fancy,</l>
                  <l>'Tis my wife, her name NANCY.</l>
                  <l>There are thoſe drink ſack in Beer-glaſſes,</l>
                  <l>Yet goe free of Poets laſhes:</l>
                  <l>Every Poët hath his Brother,</l>
                  <l>Let's not laſh one another:</l>
                  <l>We are brave fellows both,</l>
                  <l>No matter who is maſter,</l>
                  <l>So long we have the troth,</l>
                  <l>And love the Poëtaſter.</l>
                  <l>Thus much I thought for to rehearſe,</l>
                  <l>And here I write my Comment on the Verſe.</l>
                  <l>Which by your ſelf are beautifide:</l>
                  <l>Not by me villifide ♑</l>
                  <l>But rather gratifide :v</l>
                  <l>If not by you miſ-edifide</l>
                  <l>They are well fortifide <expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:rdagger"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>right †</ex>
                     </expan>
                  </l>
                  <l>As alſo well qualifide o</l>
                  <l>Which if your ſelf have juſtifide x</l>
                  <l>And from good Sack mortifide ☋</l>
                  <l>Which as yet was never certifide <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </l>
                  <l>And under your hand teſtifide :|</l>
                  <l>For which you ſhall be notefide T</l>
                  <l>Of ſuch as are ſtupefide <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </l>
                  <l>When their brains are purifide V</l>
                  <l>And with much laſhing mundifide ):</l>
                  <l>Unpared and unexemplifide (</l>
                  <l>Or at leaſt ſo much rectifide <hi>y</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>That you deſerve to be ſtilefide ⋮</l>
                  <l>And alſo ⋮ deifide</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="23" facs="tcp:104586:21"/>In the mean time your fame is magnifide ⸪</l>
                  <l>Your perſon dignifide <expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:rdagger"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>right †</ex>
                     </expan>
                  </l>
                  <l>I hope you will be ſatisfide T</l>
                  <l>When you are not damnifide X</l>
                  <l>If your fame be turpefide ):</l>
                  <l>And your pains be ladifide (</l>
                  <l>You ſhall not then be nullifide <expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:rdagger"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>right †</ex>
                     </expan>
                  </l>
                  <l>Nor yet by me ratifide (</l>
                  <l>Our work you have not mollifide <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </l>
                  <l>Nor calamities amplifide 2</l>
                  <l>And ſo my laſh is wearifide ♈</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The ſtrange explanation of the Characters.</l>
                  <l>Ϲ Kiſs my Hoſteſs, <expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:ldagger"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>left †</ex>
                     </expan> muzel her maid Ϲ rayl'd on</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                     </gap> Half drunk 2 drunk in ample manner</l>
                  <l>T To know drunk or ſober.</l>
                  <l>Thus the Verſe with quoted margent,</l>
                  <l>And ſo I end the Cloke and Sergeant.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>(He begins again)</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>W</hi> That is chidden for being halfdrunk</l>
                  <l>V To get a Fox and coſt nothing</l>
                  <l>♑ That is miſtaken in drinking</l>
                  <l>
                     <expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:rdagger"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>right †</ex>
                     </expan> That is drunk a Cup in a morning</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Qualifide:</hi> that is, Civil in drink</l>
                  <l>X That is, drink off the whole Cup</l>
                  <l>☋ That is, give over ſmall Beer</l>
                  <l>= That is, to know when to drink</l>
                  <l>☊ I have pledged the health</l>
                  <l>T Known for a good drinker</l>
                  <l>☋ Sleep after drunkenneſſe</l>
                  <l>ע Caſt in your ſtomach</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                     </gap> Begin on a Munday as doe Shoo-makers</l>
                  <l>Ϲ Fox mine Hoſt</l>
                  <l>∷ Rayl'd on for not paying the ſhot</l>
                  <l>A Hey ſtille: goe home before night</l>
                  <l>⋮ For holding out <expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:ldagger"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>left †</ex>
                     </expan> for drinking to the bottom</l>
                  <l>
                     <expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:ldagger"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>left †</ex>
                     </expan> Paying the ſhot x going on the ſcore</l>
                  <l>7: Clip the Kings Engliſh.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>REPLY.</head>
               <l>DULMAN, know I'm a Merchant more then Vintner,</l>
               <l>Though I abide at home theſe times of winter;</l>
               <l>And your torn numbers and your piece-meal rime</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n which you keep not meaſure, tune, or time,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> have receiv'd, deceiv'd, ſith you ſo ſo it,</l>
               <l>And ſith I did miſtake you for a Poët.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:104586:22"/>Kind Brother, ſith thou takeſt all upon thee,</l>
               <l>(Dear one-Cloke) much admir'd by fools, and me.</l>
               <l>Dull Rimer, know I am as much above</l>
               <l>Thy fooliſh anger, as thy flaming love.</l>
               <l>Methinks I heard thee, and thy Muſe thus mutter,</l>
               <l>(And I ſcarce heard yee, yee did both ſo ſtutter)</l>
               <l>"Hold for the Lord-ſake <hi>Nich' las,</hi> leſt you take us,</l>
               <l>"And uſe us worſe then <hi>Hercules</hi> us'd <hi>Cacus!</hi>
               </l>
               <l>But fear not, ROBIN, ſith thou know'ſt my ſpirit,</l>
               <l>And that pure love my milder breſt inherit;</l>
               <l>Nor let thy years deſpair to write agen,</l>
               <l>I'll learn a boy in five, nay, thee in ten.</l>
               <l>Thy falfc ſpell made a Comet in thy verſe,</l>
               <l>Whenas thou meant'ſt a Comment to rehearſe,</l>
               <l>Which might have made thee ſeen as well as I,</l>
               <l>That thou ſhouldſt fall great Prince of Poëtry.</l>
               <l>I wonder much that thou ſhouldſt ſo long uſe it,</l>
               <l>And take delight to ſeek to be abuſed.</l>
               <l>Your rev'rend years doe almoſt me deter</l>
               <l>From writing of your proper Character:</l>
               <l>Startle not at it, though it ſeemeth tart,</l>
               <l>'T as no more Gunpowder, then has a —</l>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head>The Character.</head>
                  <l>A Hoary head, an elocution,</l>
                  <l>As thoſe that march to execution;</l>
                  <l>And in a crowd, if one ſhould ſtrike a blow,</l>
                  <l>His brains might be ſtrook out he is ſo ſlow</l>
                  <l>In making of his juſt defence. Oh pity!</l>
                  <l>Such a bad utt'rance in a man ſo witty.</l>
                  <l>His face when I firſt ſaw, I ſaid God ſent us,</l>
                  <l>I think, th' effigies of <hi>Macelenius;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>But hear ye, mark ye me. Oh ſweeter Sire!</l>
                  <l>This man in Winter makes his dear wives fire,</l>
                  <l>And watches all the day, except one bring</l>
                  <l>Tidings V to get a Fox, and coſt nothing;</l>
                  <l>And more then this the man is a rare ſinger,</l>
                  <l>And Character'd, and T known for a good drinker;</l>
                  <l>And like the wiſer men of famous Gotham,</l>
                  <l>He is renown'd for <expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:ldagger"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>left †</ex>
                     </expan> diving to the bottom</l>
                  <l>Of the profouudeſt bowls; in fine a Greek</l>
                  <l>That doth as Shoo-makers begin with week,</l>
                  <l>And I doe fear, yet do'th' contrary wiſh,</l>
                  <l>You were half drunk <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                     </gap> clipping the Kings Engliſh,</l>
                  <l>In this your brain-ſick brain-work. O be quiet!</l>
                  <l>Or elſe goe feed upon a wittier diet:</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="25" facs="tcp:104586:22"/>And if you were drunk when you writ, go ſleep on,</l>
                  <l>Sith you were beat poor man with your own weapon.</l>
                  <l>And mark ye me, hereafter always write</l>
                  <l>Only to him whom your fierce verſes fright,</l>
                  <l>And cannot anſwer; for I ſee't is vain</l>
                  <l>To write to him can anſwer you again;</l>
                  <l>But if your folly ſhan't be ne'r forgotten</l>
                  <l>Then I will jeer you unto dead, and rotten.</l>
               </div>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head>The Epilogue.</head>
                  <l>IT may be (Gentlemen) yee'll blame me much,</l>
                  <l>That I did here enter the Liſts with ſuch;</l>
                  <l>But if a Child, or maimed man do poſt</l>
                  <l>One that contemn's him: lo! his credit's loſt,</l>
                  <l>If he accepts him not; And though they'nt gainers,</l>
                  <l>Yet it is meet to beat ſuch to good manners.</l>
                  <l>This <hi>Thing</hi> is ſuch an one: I thought my anſwer</l>
                  <l>Sufficient was; but that he was an Anſer.</l>
                  <l>Then mine unto his ſecond paper, I</l>
                  <l>Aſſuredly did think would ſatisfie;</l>
                  <l>He yet perſiſts, appointing three of's Friends</l>
                  <l>To judge of our tongue-Combate, and his ends</l>
                  <l>Of Poetry; t'was judg'd, and yet the Stint</l>
                  <l>Had a deſire to be a fool in Print.</l>
                  <l>Wherefore that I might fully pallats pleaſe</l>
                  <l>I've ſet ye here a diſh of mouldy cheeſe:</l>
                  <l>And do demand a better Champion,</l>
                  <l>Then ſuch an one, as Chevy-Chaſe did chaunt on,</l>
                  <l>Wiſhing the Reader to pronounce him yeoman,</l>
                  <l>Commanding him to ſing to babes, and women.</l>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <head>Colendiſſimo, literatiſſimoque Moecenati D. Martino <hi>HOLBEACH.</hi> The Travells: Satyr 5.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>I Muſt confeſs, dear Sir, I muſt confeſs,</l>
               <l>I'm bound to pray, that God ſtill would you bleſſe,</l>
               <l>As men obliged uſe to do; but hold,</l>
               <l>Oh fooliſh Muſe! verſes thou know'ſt ar'nt gold,</l>
               <l>And Debts are paid with coin, with lovely coine,</l>
               <l>Then I will re-pay you in your owne Coine;</l>
               <l>Was it not letters that you learnt me, ſay?</l>
               <l>Then I will pay you in the ſelfe-ſame way;</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:104586:23"/>But that can not be ſo, for ſome have ſworn</l>
               <l>That Poëts are not made, but rather born.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>I have another fetch. They ſay that friends</l>
               <l>Covet to hear their friends Adventures; ends</l>
               <l>Are but bad preſents, and I would be loth</l>
               <l>To give your longing minde leſs then whole cloth.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Since I ran from Minerva's Temple: fie,</l>
               <l>Need drove me out. Why ſhould I then ſo lie?</l>
               <l>I've ſeen the ſeventeen-headed Belgia,</l>
               <l>And that moſt fruitfull land call'd Gallia;</l>
               <l>I've ſeen alſo moſt pleaſant Germany,</l>
               <l>And in all three too much Idolatry,</l>
               <l>And Prophanation. O! who would think,</l>
               <l>Their Towns half drown'd with water, they with drink?</l>
               <l>The high and mighty States there's weakneſs in,</l>
               <l>There are ſome Heathens with moſt Chriſtian King,</l>
               <l>And the fam'd Majeſty Imperiall,</l>
               <l>In his Empire, alaſs, command's not All.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>I have obſerved, if I may it ſay,</l>
               <l>That which full many men would paſs away.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Lawrell-crown'd Caeſar, and the potent French King,</l>
               <l>With' potent States are led within a ring</l>
               <l>Of endleſs turmoils, and of laſting ſtrife,</l>
               <l>Theſe are dependants on a Princes life.</l>
               <l>Antiochus his words I verifie,</l>
               <l>"That Kingly rule is noble ſlavery;</l>
               <l>And if my Travels had as Sand's his been,</l>
               <l>I could nought ſee but vanity and Sin,</l>
               <l>With Spirits great vexation.—I lie,</l>
               <l>Sometimes I finde a minutes jollitie.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The rouling French, and throat-hoarſe Dutch I vow,</l>
               <l>Are nothing like the language us'd with you,</l>
               <l>Yours is right Caeſars right tongue, and I wiſh</l>
               <l>I had fed longer upon that ſweet diſh;</l>
               <l>Yet travell hath imboldned me, and I</l>
               <l>Have piec'd my Latin with mine Induſtry;</l>
               <l>So that I take no counſell from the Judg</l>
               <l>To give him anſwers, if he doth not grudg</l>
               <l>To ask me queſtions in the Latin tongue;</l>
               <l>But 'tis not with us, as 'tis you among,</l>
               <l>If we break Priſcian's head, we then with laughter</l>
               <l>Say 'tis chance-medley, and not dire man-ſlaughter.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Here I read all the world in Amſterdam,</l>
               <l>People of Abra'm, and th'Tartarian Cham,</l>
               <l>Hot-liver'd Spaniard, and the ſprightly French,</l>
               <l>Who dance beſt Anticks, and beſt court a wench,</l>
               <l>The ſwarthy Portugall, and to be brief,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:104586:23"/>Of all of Babels languages the chief;</l>
               <l>Only I muſt make bold to make intruſion,</l>
               <l>There's order here, as there was wilde confuſion;</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And here are ſome things too which are moſt vile,</l>
               <l>And ſome things which doe make my worſhip ſmile.</l>
               <l>A man may gnaw, walking i'th' Streets if 'ts clear,</l>
               <l>He ſha'nt be Burgemaſter the next year.</l>
               <l>They'r far from pride, for they call ev'ry man</l>
               <l>(Without Sir) by's name; or Tom, or Sam,</l>
               <l>With Uncle to't, or Father; and I've heard</l>
               <l>An old man call a childe Father; deterr'd</l>
               <l>I was to hear it, leſt the good Old man</l>
               <l>Was out his Wits by ſome ſmart-gnawing pain.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And now they ſlay their Brethren; ev'ry Boor,</l>
               <l>And Shop-keeper hath one ſlain at his door;</l>
               <l>So that I thought the men were Butchers all;</l>
               <l>Yet Sattin-doublets ſcarce became the Stall.</l>
               <l>They're of opinion too, that th'Sabbath-day</l>
               <l>Was n't made to work, but for a worſe thing, P'ay:</l>
               <l>Accordingly they ramble out the Town</l>
               <l>To give their Wives and Sweet-hearts a green-gown;</l>
               <l>And if a man ſays unto you <hi>Avou,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>He never meant the Cann ſhould come to you;</l>
               <l>But playeth childrens play; and is it ſo</l>
               <l>Said I? then mine out of my hands ſha'nt go;</l>
               <l>And if there be a quarrel or a ſtrife,</l>
               <l>Then it muſt be decided by the Knife.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But this Ile ſay, and this truth me affords,</l>
               <l>They are true hearts, the French-men but meer words;</l>
               <l>They have more good too, for they all employ</l>
               <l>That filthy idleneſs would elſe deſtroy.</l>
               <l>They ſhame moſt Nations by their Induſtry,</l>
               <l>And with them is the trueſt Palmiſtry;</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>or they can ſee what Fortunes men ſhall have,</l>
               <l>As he by's lab'rous hands doth gain or ſave;</l>
               <l>They make all Children Children, and the young'ſt</l>
               <l>Muſt ſhare the greateſt ſhare the reſt amongſt;</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>or th'oldeſt are brought up, and they do'nt ſpy</l>
               <l>What help Brethren doe give, no more doe I.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The French exceed in Complemency, and</l>
               <l>Men ſhould in all things ſometimes make a ſtand:</l>
               <l>They're ſuperſtitious too, and Phariſees;</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>or in the ſtreets to pray, they'll ſwarm like Bees</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n their Proceſſions; and the Peaſants</l>
               <l>To ſpeak the truth are meer, meer, meer pedants;</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ut th' Gentry are the mapps of Curteſie,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd the deſervers of Nobilitie.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:104586:24"/>Thus if I ſhow not Learning, nor Fancy,</l>
               <l>Nor by all ſtyled noble Induſtry,</l>
               <l>Nor prov'd affection, I think no leſs,</l>
               <l>But that you ſee a ſtriving thankfullneſſe</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>In your ſervant N. M.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <head>The Epitaph upon the right worſhipfull <hi>Thomas Slany</hi> Mayor of <hi>Lyn.</hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <l>STay Paſſenger, and let thy trav'ling ey</l>
               <l>Read here lie's all the frail mortality</l>
               <l>Of a good Mayor, and prudent Captain,</l>
               <l>Induſtrious Merchant, who did ſcrue the main</l>
               <l>In ſuch long voyages, that I prefer</l>
               <l>Him an imbetter'd, far-gone Traveller</l>
               <l>Here lies a Saint: I lye, for his ſweet ſpirit</l>
               <l>Is gone to God where it ſhall ever inherit</l>
               <l>Inceſſant joyes; and in frail fleſh all ſpy</l>
               <l>There can not be an intire ſanctity,</l>
               <l>So that the Saint's in Heav'n: but behold here</l>
               <l>Doth lie a well-belov'd Commiſſioner</l>
               <l>Of ill-belov'd Exciſe, a true black Swan,</l>
               <l>And yet unſpotted, conſcientious man.</l>
               <l>Here lies the man of approv'd moderation,</l>
               <l>Alas, we want ſuch Pillars in our Nation!</l>
               <l>Here lies the true great Almner of the poor,</l>
               <l>And therefore cruell Death was their undoer,</l>
               <l>Ah! for that which he did, was but a part</l>
               <l>Of that which was reſolved in his heart;</l>
               <l>But being now diſſolved, oh receivers</l>
               <l>Of God, the poor are calld, I fear deceivers</l>
               <l>Of expectation will promiſe ſuch;</l>
               <l>But when they dy will not give halfe ſo much.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Anag.</hi> Proud Death hath ſlain this man although ſo deer,</l>
               <l>And in contempt of mortals nayls him here.</l>
               <l>His knowledge came from Heaven, and thereto</l>
               <l>Did lend whan here he did intend to do.</l>
               <l>I doubt whether he gave, or elſe receiv'd</l>
               <l>More honour by his Gown with juſtice reav'd.</l>
               <l>He loved publick peace, although his ſtars</l>
               <l>Allotted him to live in home-bred warres.</l>
               <l>He was hated (although it ſeemeth rov'd;</l>
               <l>Becauſe he could not be enough belov'd.</l>
               <l>To others good he was intent ſo much,</l>
               <l>That he ſeem'd to neglect himſelfe, None ſuch!</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:104586:24"/>He overcame himſelfe, and left to try</l>
               <l>Whether he liv'd, or dy'd more piouſly?</l>
               <l>He wrung tears from envy it ſelf now ſlain,</l>
               <l>And lives in mouths, and minds of men again.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <head>An <hi>Elegy</hi> on the death of Mr. <hi>William Barnard,</hi> Son of <hi>John Barnard</hi> of Kingſton upon <hi>Hull <abbr>Eſq</abbr>
               </hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <l>VVIll Pens lie ſtill when ſuch a Subject is</l>
               <l>Of our approaching miſery, though his Bliſs?</l>
               <l>Can Poets ſilent be when Prophets dye?</l>
               <l>Or was his death without a myſtery?</l>
               <l>Oh, would there had been ſuch a conſtant race</l>
               <l>In ſome Arch-Biſhops of their ſcanted Grace!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Amired ſeaventeen! that melts the ey</l>
               <l>Of Englands Eye, the Vniverſity.</l>
               <l>Spirituall, and yet by Phlegme o're come,</l>
               <l>Who when of God diſputing, all were dumb!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Friends can't but grieve, that thou comming to Town,</l>
               <l>Paſſ'd by their Houſes, and did'ſt lay thee down</l>
               <l>At thine old Inne the Star; thou mind'ſt thy way</l>
               <l>So much that thou would'ſt not make any ſtay.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And like great Alexander, who did aver</l>
               <l>Himſelfe to be the Son of Jupiter,</l>
               <l>And not of Philip; ſo thou ſeemed'ſt here,</l>
               <l>To own Jehovah, leave thy Father deare.</l>
               <l>Alas! I can not make Cities to mourne</l>
               <l>With level'd walls in griefe exceſſive torne</l>
               <l>By Alexander for his dear friends death</l>
               <l>Nor in Panegyricks to ſpend my breath</l>
               <l>As th' Ancients did; yet I will raiſe a Tomb</l>
               <l>Sall laſt untill the laſt of dayes do come;</l>
               <l>Shall live when Marble dies: Theſe numbers here</l>
               <l>Shall on Record in th' daies to come appeare.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Oh, this 'tis to be good! the rotten waies</l>
               <l>Of ſome leud youths deſerve not theſe our Baies.</l>
               <l>Is there one more in th' Vniverſity,</l>
               <l>Nay in the univerſe ſo good as He?</l>
               <l>England, thou want'ſt more Barnards; —oh, that I</l>
               <l>Might live, and dye, oh God, ſo holily!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Ah, had'ſt thou liv'd, thy Life would have made Rules</l>
               <l>For Graduats, and made the moſt bear Gules</l>
               <l>Within their Faces for the obvious ſhame,</l>
               <l>That would accoaſt them hearing of thy Fame.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:104586:25"/>Thou that amaz'd the Schoolmen, commonly</l>
               <l>In moſt diſcourſe preaching Divinity.</l>
               <l>Throw down thy Quill, my Muſe, and pray have don,</l>
               <l>'Tis vain to put a Candle to the Sun.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <head>An ACROSTICK.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>W</hi>—It ſo refin'd, as th'purer Gold, ſo priz'd;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>I</hi>—ngenuous, that men Him Idoliz'd.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>L</hi>—aw both Divine and Humane he much knew;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>L</hi>—earning beyond his Years (God knows) but few:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>I</hi>—ngenious, and then apply't to merit:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>A</hi>—miable, whoſe ſweet Diviner ſpirit</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>M</hi>—ajeſty great and comely did inherit.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>B</hi>—eauty of Holineſs poſſeſt his heart;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>A</hi>—rts were in him (wonder!) beyond all Art:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>R</hi>—ighteouſneſs dwelt within his Soul. His Pen</l>
               <l>(<hi>N</hi>—aſo-like) wonne the hearts of Learned men.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>A</hi>—rms he bore againſt Vice: As forc'd with charms,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>R</hi>—eading good Authors: Fit 'gainſt Luſts alarms;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>D</hi>—oing (the beſt of Cures) and yet no harms.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <head>EPITAPH.</head>
            <l>HEre lies grave Youth, Wiſdom ſublime,</l>
            <l>Second devout S. BERNARD in his Time.</l>
            <l>A Sophiſter, yet hating Sophiſtry;</l>
            <l>(If I ſhould ſay his Spirit lies here, I ly)</l>
            <l>Some Doctors Freſhmen are compar'd with Him,</l>
            <l>And their great Lights compar'd with His are dim.</l>
            <l>If Scholars ask what his Degree was; even</l>
            <l>This young-old Saint commenc'd not here, but 'n Heav'n.</l>
            <l>Such Sons, ſuch Scholars, and ſuch Saints as He,</l>
            <l>Are not for Men but for the Deity:</l>
            <l>And if thou'dſt know (Reader) who here doth ly,</l>
            <l>Here lies a Man to judg an Angel by.</l>
            <l>One ſo prepar'd for Death: that (certainly)</l>
            <l>Brave Soul, he only took one day to dye;</l>
            <l>Yet, Reader, thou maiſt ſtill inquire whoſe Tombe 17.</l>
            <l>This is; then thou ſhalt know at th'day of doome. 17.</l>
            <l>His years in number to theſe numbers come. 17.</l>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:104586:25"/>
            <head>Elegij-Epithalamion: To his indeared Bro. in Law <hi>T. S.</hi> on the death of his CHILD.</head>
            <l>SWeet babe, I do admire thy wiſer courſe,</l>
            <l>That to end pain had ſo timely recourſe</l>
            <l>Vnto the way of laſting happineſſe</l>
            <l>By Death who unto Heav'n the Uſher is;</l>
            <l>"For Life's a froſt of cold felicity,</l>
            <l>"And Death a thaw of all our miſery;</l>
            <l>Thou'rt freed from freezing winters, ſummers parchings,</l>
            <l>Thirſt, hunger, anger, ſorrow, love, hate, things</l>
            <l>Which make life miſerable; now curſd War,</l>
            <l>And fearfull peſtilence are from thee far:</l>
            <l>Both mind, and Carkaſſe pihching poverty</l>
            <l>Don't interrupt thy bleſt tranquility;</l>
            <l>Vice-drawing Riches in thy ſtation</l>
            <l>Can not delude thee by temptation;</l>
            <l>Inchanting beauty though never ſo brave</l>
            <l>By all her ſleights can thee not now enſlave,</l>
            <l>And now ear-tickling, and heart-ſwelling Fame</l>
            <l>Can't make thee proud to get a glorious name.</l>
            <l>Ambitious honour can't ſwell up thy mind</l>
            <l>To leave the taunt of Treaſon vile behind.</l>
            <l>Luſt, Pride, nor Avarice, Sloth, Drunkennes,</l>
            <l>Slander nor any thing can thee unbleſſe.</l>
            <l>"Long uſe of life is as a lingring foe,</l>
            <l>"And gentle Death the only end of woe;</l>
            <l>And this in all mens eyes ſurely ſeem's plaine,</l>
            <l>Life is but loſt, where Death is counted gaine.</l>
            <l>The longer life, the greater is our guilt,</l>
            <l>Life muſt by life be paid, and ſo life's ſpilt.</l>
            <l>Thou could'ſt not bear the burden of diſtreſs,</l>
            <l>Therefore this life to thee were wretchedneſſe.</l>
            <l>We firſt do bud, then bloom, then ſeed, laſt fall</l>
            <l>So do our ſhaddows turn nothing at all.</l>
            <l>Wherefore thy death no Elegy com's on;</l>
            <l>But a joyfull Epithalamion;</l>
            <l>Or if we be ſo fooliſh, as to weep,</l>
            <l>Thou do'ſt thy joyings in the Heavens keep,</l>
            <l>Which was created glorious, and which</l>
            <l>Is delectable, beautifull, and rich;</l>
            <l>For habitation comfortable; for</l>
            <l>There the King Chriſt is, the Law love, th' Honour</l>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:104586:26"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:104586:26"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:104586:27"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:104586:27"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <l>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:104586:28"/>Pure verity, the Peace felicity,</l>
            <l>The moſt ſweet life, laſting Eternity.</l>
            <l>There's light without darkneſs; mirth without ſadneſs;</l>
            <l>True health without fleſh-conſuming ſickneſs;</l>
            <l>Wealth without want; credit without diſgrace;</l>
            <l>Beauty without blemiſh, (not on a face;)</l>
            <l>Eaſe without labour; riches without ruſt;</l>
            <l>(Nothing that frets is there, nor dirt, nor duſt)</l>
            <l>Beatitude 'thout miſery God lends;</l>
            <l>And conſolation that never ends.</l>
            <l>Now I am not content, but faſt reſolved,</l>
            <l>When God doth ſee his time, to be diſſolved.</l>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <div type="part">
               <head>Elegie on one H<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>NT a Groom, ſlain by his fellow-ſervant (being unarmed) upon ſome words, he having in haſte (other ſervants being abſent) carried his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter a baſon of water, before Gentlemen, with his Doublet off.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>To Sir <hi>R.S.</hi>
                  </salute>
               </opener>
               <lg>
                  <l>GRieve not, dear Sir; for what man e'r could vaunt,</l>
                  <l>That he had never a raſh, fooliſh Servant?</l>
                  <l>Or what man, though he were full wiſe and holy,</l>
                  <l>But in his Houſe ſometimes hath hapned folly?</l>
                  <l>What was Amnon's unto his ſiſter, oh!</l>
                  <l>Why then doe you torment your Spirit ſo?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>I ſhould have thought (his doublet off) he might</l>
                  <l>Before have thought upon this ſimple fight:</l>
                  <l>But then we ſhould have found him better armed,</l>
                  <l>And then the Knave had not the fool ſo harmed.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thou Varlet, Coward, Irchin, Mans-ſhame, weaſell,</l>
                  <l>Couldeſt thou armed, fight one arm'd with Heaſell?</l>
                  <l>Oh unheard of puſillanimity!</l>
                  <l>And, oh, unparalleld ſimplicity!</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Where were the noble Spirits, and the hands,</l>
                  <l>That us'd to combate it on Callis ſands?</l>
                  <l>They us'd to change their weapons, and to ſee,</l>
                  <l>Moſt nobly, that their lengths did'nt diſagree;</l>
                  <l>Or have their Seconds, or their Surgions</l>
                  <l>To ſearch them, and their arms: but out upon's!</l>
                  <l>That e'r blood ran in veins ſo baſe, ignoble,</l>
                  <l>Or that a Sword was drawn by ſuch a bable!</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And, oh, thou Coxcomb Groom, that wer't fore-warned</l>
                  <l>By h s Duel-like words, and not fore-armed!</l>
                  <l>For, if thou hadſt had with thee temper'd ſteel,</l>
                  <l>You both might have been heard, and yet not feel—</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="33" facs="tcp:104586:28"/>Each others blows, and (now) that fatall day</l>
                  <l>Might happy been, in parting of the fray.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Good God? what thing is man, that breaks thy laws</l>
                  <l>For matters of poor flyes, or meaner ſtraws?</l>
                  <l>Such Cainabals ſure are incorrigible;</l>
                  <l>For thou forbad'ſt it e'r ſince Cain kil'd Abel.</l>
                  <l>Thou wretched Dueller, now that good Tree,</l>
                  <l>(That wonted was) cannot (now) ſhelter Thee:</l>
                  <l>For (now) it not only can't ſhelter Thee,</l>
                  <l>But pours received water (now) upon Thee!</l>
                  <l>Wherefore we ſee, to perpetrate a Duell,</l>
                  <l>Before both God and Man is to doe-ill.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>EPITAPH.</head>
               <l>Here lies one, whom Death did HUNT</l>
               <l>From the womb unto the Font;</l>
               <l>Watching him at advantages,</l>
               <l>With naked ſword he at him flyes:</l>
               <l>And be'ng a WALKER he out-ran,</l>
               <l>And wounded mortally this Man.</l>
               <l>I thought the Groom had not been able</l>
               <l>T'have ſhunn'd the danger of the Stable</l>
               <l>By furious Horſes: But, alaſs,</l>
               <l>Thoſe ſcap'd; he was ſlain by an Aſs!</l>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <head>An Elegie upon the Death of my Daughter <hi>Amy.</hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <l>I Am not as that Emperor, who did</l>
               <l>The nuntios of the death of's Son forbid</l>
               <l>To be made known by's Spouſe, or by his Servant;</l>
               <l>And therefore ſhe by ſable weeds did plant</l>
               <l>That knowledg in his troubled head. Nor as</l>
               <l>The King <note n="†" place="margin">Aegeus</note> that (but ſuſpecting his childe, was</l>
               <l>Deſtroy'd) ſeeing the Ships blacker, come as</l>
               <l>By ſhadow of the Sun, or age, alaſs!</l>
               <l>Did from a rock, his Son then ſayling by,</l>
               <l>Add to his Triumph, a ſad Tragedy.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Nor as one of our <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>R.</hi> 2.</note> Kings; whoſe paſſion</l>
               <l>For his loſt Lady, made him ſo far gon</l>
               <l>In a kind of wilde frenzy, for to raze,</l>
               <l>And make a Chaos and confuſed Maze</l>
               <l>O'th' Houſe where Death her ſtrook: yet I can grieve,</l>
               <l>(Dear Babe) that God didn't give thee a reprieve</l>
               <l>For ſome few years, ſith I am confident</l>
               <l>My ſins thee from this Earth away have rent.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:104586:29"/>Ah! how I ſigh that Beautie's rivall is</l>
               <l>Converted to the poor impurer aſhes!</l>
               <l>That Globe-like face, thoſe twinkling ſtarrs thine eyes,</l>
               <l>That Angel's face, that front that did ariſe</l>
               <l>Like Heavens milky way, thoſe purer hands</l>
               <l>That would have bound Gallants in am'rous bands,</l>
               <l>If thou had'ſt liv'd; that aequall ſymetry</l>
               <l>That made men judge thee pure Divinity,</l>
               <l>"And truly I do think of worſe and leſſe,</l>
               <l>The Heathen's made them Gods, and Godeſſes.</l>
               <l>Who ever ſaw ſuch matron looks? ſuch ſmiles?</l>
               <l>Such ſpeaking actions? woman-childiſh wiles</l>
               <l>To make her ſelfe diſport? but oh! I make</l>
               <l>My ſelfe new griefe, and make my heart re-ake!</l>
               <l>In meditating of thy change ſo faſt</l>
               <l>By a Conſumption that thou ſeem'd to faſt,</l>
               <l>Whoſe body was ſo light it might have gone</l>
               <l>To Heaven without a reſurrection.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>So frail a thing is fleſh! ſo have I ſeen</l>
               <l>The Princely Roſe, the fragrant flowers Queen</l>
               <l>Hon'ring a Garden one day, and the next</l>
               <l>Look pale like one with anger much perplex'd.</l>
               <l>Ah! here I ſee ſeeming Angelick beauty;</l>
               <l>A watry buble, vanity, a ly!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>I think't not meet to tear the Earth's moyſt womb</l>
               <l>To make thee a too large half Acre Tomb,</l>
               <l>Nor am I able, nor as Hatton's is</l>
               <l>Above the Houſe a mounting Pyramis.</l>
               <l>What profit's thee a ſheet of Lead? what good</l>
               <l>If on thy Courſe a Marble quarry ſtood?</l>
               <l>Long, and large Epitaphs what good have they?</l>
               <l>They're but accounted meer Tautology.</l>
               <l>And Epitaph's (I think) upon the dead</l>
               <l>Are better farre not written then not read.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <head>The EPITAPH.</head>
            <l>HEre lie's wiſe and beauteous duſt,</l>
            <l>Ah, for mortality hath ruſt!</l>
            <l>Beauteous, if Ingredients be</l>
            <l>The ruddy-Roſe and white Lilly.</l>
            <l>Wiſe to dye, ſith Life was pain,</l>
            <l>And Death in Chriſt, not loſſe but gain.</l>
            <l>Laſtly a myſt'ry was adoing,</l>
            <l>In nine moneths comming, nine moneths going,</l>
            <l>And as nine Muſes verſes ſhowing.</l>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="35" facs="tcp:104586:29"/>
            <head>Elegie by the Author unto his yoak-fellow from beyond the Seas.</head>
            <l>I Know thou can not chooſe but laugh to ſee,</l>
            <l>That I again in verſe do now court Thee:</l>
            <l>When you ſhould court with due obedience</l>
            <l>They ſay, poor men! that of it's want of ſenſe,</l>
            <l>However men don't uſe a ſiege to lay</l>
            <l>Vnto that Town that give's them peacefull way:</l>
            <l>But I from Amiana now apart</l>
            <l>Muſt ſtay; yet Heav'n doth know ſhee ha's my heart.</l>
            <l>Oh! ſee our Heavenly Father now will have</l>
            <l>That unreſt that thy earthly once us gave,</l>
            <l>We muſt not for a time enjoy each other,</l>
            <l>Which makes me think on that which you do ſmother</l>
            <l>In dark oblivion. The pleaſant Nights!</l>
            <l>That you, and I performed Lovers rights</l>
            <l>In giving each the other's ſoul, and yet</l>
            <l>Thou never foundſt me luſtfull Marmorit,</l>
            <l>Nor I thee Helen; for I dare proteſt</l>
            <l>Our purer loves could well indure the teſt</l>
            <l>Of continency, and of conſtancy;</l>
            <l>For frowning Friends could never make us lie.</l>
            <l>And Heavens beſt know thou might'ſt Adonis be</l>
            <l>For any knowledg that I had of Thee,</l>
            <l>Or an Hermophrodite, and thou I know</l>
            <l>Diddeſt not know if I were man, or no,</l>
            <l>Or a virago Metamorphized,</l>
            <l>Which would betray lawfull pleaſures in bed.</l>
            <l>Well thou the load-ſtone; I the Iron was,</l>
            <l>Thou loved'ſt me, and I no Debtor was.</l>
            <l>What harm did we by out immortall love?</l>
            <l>We taught falſe lovers fraud for to remove.</l>
            <l>"What Merchant's ſhips have our ſwelling ſighs drown'd?</l>
            <l>"Who ſay's our teares have over-flow'd his ground?</l>
            <l>Methink's this ſhould be comfort to you now,</l>
            <l>He that you truſted did hold truth with you.</l>
            <l>Indeed it griev'd me that the babe ſhould be</l>
            <l>So ſick, as when I parted laſt from thee,</l>
            <l>A babe ſo like us both, that they do ſay</l>
            <l>She is her Father's picture, then ſay they</l>
            <l>She is not ſo, ſhe's like her mother; troth</l>
            <l>Say'th the wiſeſt, I think ſhe's like them both,</l>
            <l>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:104586:30"/>And thou ſay'ſt (pars pro toto) if ſhe dy,</l>
            <l>Then thou poor ſoul within her grave muſt ly.</l>
            <l>But pry thee think of Abram's faith, and truſt;</l>
            <l>For Abram's faith, entit'led Abram juſt:</l>
            <l>When God had bid him ſacrifice his Son,</l>
            <l>His only Son, and he would have it done;</l>
            <l>But God prepar'd a Lamb, ſince he had try'd</l>
            <l>That Abram's outward ſhew had not bely'd</l>
            <l>His heart; wherefore truſt in him, and thou'lt ſee,</l>
            <l>His Providence upon both her and mee.</l>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <head>The INN.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>IF I be (Gentlemen) in my will croſt,</l>
               <l>And cannot wait on you, pray read your Hoſt,</l>
               <l>Whoſe Muſe (ſuch as it is) preſum'd herein,</l>
               <l>To ſpeak ſomewhat of him, Servants and Inn;</l>
               <l>And though I ſoar not, ſorry I ſhould be,</l>
               <l>Sith here's no wit, if not ſome induſtry;</l>
               <l>And I doe this intreat, and only ſo,</l>
               <l>Read it if ye have nothing elſe to doe;</l>
               <l>For ye know well by LAW it is in USE,</l>
               <l>And therefore GOOD, not BAD (if no abuſe.)</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>LAWFULL Sith in the ſacred Word we ſee</l>
               <l>To Wayfarers ſuch place appointed bee;</l>
               <l>And who with it a cavil dare beginn,</l>
               <l>Sith God the Word hath taken up his Inn?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Then uſe it well, and not uſe ill your ſelves;</l>
               <l>For that is it which makes your Ships but ſhelves.</l>
               <l>Beſt things abuſed we know are made bad,</l>
               <l>Wine made to make the heavie, ſad heart glad,</l>
               <l>If too much taken cauſeth Drunkenneſs,</l>
               <l>And Gluttony proceeds from meats exceſs.</l>
               <l>Meet veſtures doted on, all men deride,</l>
               <l>And beaſts old cloaths ill-us'd, are turn'd to Pride:</l>
               <l>But this infers not that we uſe no wine,</l>
               <l>Or that we ſhould not breakfaſt, ſup, or dine,</l>
               <l>Or that becauſe fine Clothes make fond fools proud,</l>
               <l>We ſhould uſe Heav'ns tapeſtry, a Cloud,</l>
               <l>And nothing elſe to cover us. Oh no!</l>
               <l>For you may ſafely herein further go:</l>
               <l>But uſe it lawfully, and there's no flaw;</l>
               <l>For 'tis allowed by the Common-Law.</l>
               <l>Only he that intends to keep an Inn,</l>
               <l>Muſt pray to God to keep out entring Sin.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:104586:30"/>VSEFVL if Merchants bargain, or if they</l>
               <l>Are gath'ring up their Bargains fruits onth' way,</l>
               <l>And there on equal termes two parties meet,</l>
               <l>(That cannot friendly ſee each in the Street)</l>
               <l>And have their bus'neſs arbitrated; ſince</l>
               <l>Each man in's Houſe hath a preheminence.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>It tels us that we are but Travailers,</l>
               <l>And that our Journey tends unto the Stars.</l>
               <l>And that we have not an abiding home,</l>
               <l>Untill we doe unto Olympus come.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Far Travailers can tell ye th'benefit</l>
               <l>Of a good Inn, and giv't that Epethite:</l>
               <l>Nay, I am not the firſt that did beginn</l>
               <l>To ſay, nothing's more uſeful then an Inn —</l>
               <l>When fiery Sol doth parch the moiſtning humor,</l>
               <l>When to quench thirſt, the Trav'ler is a fumer,</l>
               <l>When tedious way hath toyld the new-come gueſt,</l>
               <l>He finding welcom, how ſweet is his reſt!</l>
               <l>When SANDS in's Travails in wilde ſands had been,</l>
               <l>How welcome then was his oft-wiſhed Inn!</l>
               <l>And ye are here as welcom, if ye pleaſe.</l>
               <l>Or e'r you were in all your paſſed dayes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But to proceed, uſeful was that Hoſteſs</l>
               <l>(At firſt as they ſay) but of Holineſs,</l>
               <l>And honour a ſweet Lady HELENA,</l>
               <l>Who was the truly-beauteous Coelia,</l>
               <l>Not ignorant of the Wayfarer's curer;</l>
               <l>Good Hoſteſs; for Phyſitian n'er was ſurer.</l>
               <l>Good Hoſteſs, that would be a Stable-keeper,</l>
               <l>So in her heart of Chriſt ſhee might be keeper.</l>
               <l>Thus ye ſee Holineſs came from an Inn,</l>
               <l>And a brave Noble-man (ye know) was ſeen</l>
               <l>To love and court the Daughter of an Hoſt</l>
               <l>With honour too, and thought his love not loſt;</l>
               <l>For worth is found in them by worthies oft,</l>
               <l>Although for bad ones, good ones oft are ſcoft;</l>
               <l>Nay, rev'rend DOD ſaid once he had been loſt,</l>
               <l>If great Jehovah had not been his Hoſt.</l>
               <l>Who's that that cals me, would you have me fly?</l>
               <l>The other two you ſhall have by and by.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>NOT BAD, for here your Hoſt ſha'nt draw you on</l>
               <l>To loſe your time by baſe deluſion,</l>
               <l>Your Hoſteſs neither ſhew her ſelf ſo wild,</l>
               <l>As of her honeſty to be beguil'd.</l>
               <l>The Drawer ſhall not with-draw what is due</l>
               <l>In meaſure in the half pints that enſue.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:104586:31"/>The Tapſter neither by his fraud, nor ſloth</l>
               <l>Shall dare to bum your Jugg with cheating froth.</l>
               <l>The Maid ſha'nt ſhow with a laſcivious Art</l>
               <l>That leachery doth harbour in her heart.</l>
               <l>And the Hoſt'ler ſhall be no Oat-ſtealer:</l>
               <l>But to your ſpeechles horſes a juſt dealer.</l>
               <l>What ſervant have I that dare others prompt,</l>
               <l>Or doe't himſelfe to add to your Accompt?</l>
               <l>And for my ſelfe, and ſecond take my word,</l>
               <l>Our conſciences will not ſuch Acts afford.</l>
               <l>Only as ye are dealt by; ſo I pray,</l>
               <l>For what ye call, and have ye'll pleaſe to pay.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>BUT GOOD. For Sabboth-dayes ſhan't be prophan'd,</l>
               <l>Although the wider world thereby be gain'd;</l>
               <l>And curſing, ſwearing, and ſuch God-les deeds,</l>
               <l>I doe deſire to pluck up, as bad weeds.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But if you lodge, or bargain, or be merry,</l>
               <l>You having Beer, tobacco, and my Sherry,</l>
               <l>Canary, Malligo, French-wine, or what</l>
               <l>My Houſe afford's, if ye accept but that</l>
               <l>In civill waies; for oh! Il'd not begin</l>
               <l>To anſwer for another man's groſs ſin!</l>
               <l>And gray-coat, bare-coat ſhall have due reſpect,</l>
               <l>Only thereby no Gentlemen neglect.</l>
               <l>Whereby I hope our ſtarre terreſtriall</l>
               <l>Shal prove it ſelfe truly coeleſtiall,</l>
               <l>And (Gentlemen) at your peculiar coſt,</l>
               <l>Ye're wellcome kindly to your younger Hoſt:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And ſince his Inn's ſo good, oh be ſo good!</l>
               <l>As not to drown your Hoſt within a flood</l>
               <l>Of wild and mercileſſe ſtrong Beer, and Wine;</l>
               <l>For if ye do, the fault will not be mine,</l>
               <l>If ſervants ſerve you badly, for my eye</l>
               <l>Make's gueſts all times ſerved obſervantly,</l>
               <l>Nay, if ye force your Hoſt to be a Cupper,</l>
               <l>Your Hoſteſs abſent, ye may loſe your ſupper:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Laſtly I have adventur'd oft by Sea;</l>
               <l>But fear 'tis greater now to uſe this Plea;</l>
               <l>For ſome men have ſuch uncontrouled ſpirits,</l>
               <l>That at my words they'll rave like Bedlamites.</l>
               <l>Thus your Hoſt ſhow's in his Poetick mood</l>
               <l>His <hi>Inn Lawfull, Vſefull, not Bad but good.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The end of the Morall Poems.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>NE PLUS ULTRA.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="invocation">
            <pb n="39" facs="tcp:104586:31"/>
            <p>TRIN-UNI DEO, SACRUM. In nomine Sacro Sanctae &amp; individuae Trinitatis, <hi>AMEN.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="40" facs="tcp:104586:32"/>
            <head>Long-ſuffering.</head>
            <l>THe Hawk preys on the trembling Partridge, and</l>
            <l>Chickens doe feel the Kites harſh hand,</l>
            <l>The ſmaller freſh-fiſh that doe haunt the Dike,</l>
            <l>Are juſtly fearfull of the Pike.</l>
            <l>The Fiſh at Sea, that have not ſtrength their Bulwark,</l>
            <l>Doe tremble much for fear o'th' Shark.</l>
            <l>The ſtronger beaſts the weaker e'r did rule,</l>
            <l>The ſurly Lion bangs the Mule.</l>
            <l>Great Princes caſtigate (oft-times) the leſs,</l>
            <l>The ſtrong man beats the weak t'exceſs.</l>
            <l>But, O my God, I skill not theſe thy wayes!</l>
            <l>Thou doſt deſerve our bounden praiſe!</l>
            <l>Thou that to Attoms couldſt the world convert,</l>
            <l>In a ſhort time, as thou in making wer't.</l>
            <l>Thou that couldſt take the breath out of the Noſtrill,</l>
            <l>Which we, O God, doe daily feel;</l>
            <l>Who art diſpleaſed with our hainous ſin,</l>
            <l>Thy mercies, Lord, doſt not hold in. —</l>
            <l>Is this th'manner of men, oh my Lord God!</l>
            <l>What man forgives with power ſhod?</l>
            <l>And can it be my God doth ſtill forgive!</l>
            <l>I will leave ſin then, if I live.</l>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <head>SHIPWRACK, OR, An Elegie on the Drowning of <hi>John Olly,</hi> and his whole Company at Sea, by the overwhelming of his Ship, &amp;c.</head>
            <l>I Can't diſpute what was the cauſe the Ship</l>
            <l>Wreſtling with Ocean ſhould receive this trip.</l>
            <l>I know the Northern Seas are dangerous,</l>
            <l>Men ſay the Maſter was too covetous;</l>
            <l>But I ſee many doe arrive their Port,</l>
            <l>And judg the other barely a report.</l>
            <l>Some think the Ship was ill-conditioned,</l>
            <l>And from the Sea did turn her crazy head,</l>
            <l>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:104586:32"/>Oh God, thou knowſt the cauſe, and only thou</l>
            <l>Who letteſt ſome paſs in, and ſome paſs through—</l>
            <l>The ſurly waves. Oh that we here beneath</l>
            <l>Could think we were within an inch of death,</l>
            <l>When in a Ship! But the contagion</l>
            <l>To thoſe us'd to't, is never thought upon.</l>
            <l>Perhaps, ô God, ſome in the Ship might think</l>
            <l>Their drink their God; therefore thou gav'ſt them drink.</l>
            <l>Perhaps, ſome thought their goods their God, ô brave!</l>
            <l>And therefore thou ſaidſt, Let your Gods ye ſave,</l>
            <l>Whom ye adore; and without queſtion</l>
            <l>This thing was given us to look upon</l>
            <l>With more then common eyes; of good 'tis full,</l>
            <l>It ſhews thee Juſt and alſo Mercifull.</l>
            <l>Juſt, for thou art juſt in all theſe thy ways,</l>
            <l>And for thy Mercy, Lord, we muſt thee praiſe.</l>
            <l>What? but one moment thinking the Ship ſafe,</l>
            <l>And in another, poſt the help o'th' weaf!</l>
            <l>Merchant and Maſter might think on Lynn Haven</l>
            <l>But now: now taking of a voyage to Heaven.</l>
            <l>Oh thou, my ſoul, take thou a great remorſe</l>
            <l>On thoſe that truſt (vain truſt) in Ships of force.</l>
            <l>Her Ordnance that ſometime doe ſtand in ſteed,</l>
            <l>Now in the Storm might doe the fatall deed.</l>
            <l>Oh the ſad ſhreik of the poor Company,</l>
            <l>That now, now, now muſt dye ſo mis'rably!</l>
            <l>How did Death ſit within their looks? was there</l>
            <l>Time to make their Repentance true, ſincere?</l>
            <l>Was there none ſwearing in that dang'rous Storm?</l>
            <l>Or did the fear of Death them all transform?</l>
            <l>Yet, Lord, thy wayes of Providence we hallow;</l>
            <l>For thou ſometimes receiv'ſt ſouls from the gallow;</l>
            <l>And theſe might have, as large warning i'th' Storm;</l>
            <l>Alike the Deluge gen'rall Microcoſm;</l>
            <l>The waters came on them e'r they aware were,</l>
            <l>So did thy hand, oh Lord! finde them out here;</l>
            <l>And I fear, Lord, that thou haſt ſpared us,</l>
            <l>Who are for guilt as meritorious.</l>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <head>PAIN.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>WHen Pain oppreſſes me, and my heart heaves,</l>
               <l>O Lord, thraſh out ſome Corn out of theſe ſheaves.</l>
               <l>When I ſhriek out, oh God!</l>
               <l>Scourg'd with thy ſharper Rod,</l>
               <l>Let t'be for Sin,</l>
               <l>I ſigh within!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:104586:33"/>
               <l>When my Pain makes me ſigh, O good Lord, oh!</l>
               <l>Oh then let Grace in my heart further goe,</l>
               <l>And work ſome greater good,</l>
               <l>To think upon thy blood,</l>
               <l>Which for me bled,</l>
               <l>For me was ſhed.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>When thou afflicteſt me with thine own hand,</l>
               <l>Who millions to ſerve thee canſt command,</l>
               <l>My Sins themſelves preſent,</l>
               <l>Oh then incontinent,</l>
               <l>Then let my ſpirit</l>
               <l>Apply thy merit.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>When I am weak'ned, and am overcome;</l>
               <l>Yet let me not in praiſes e'r be dumbe,</l>
               <l>For my ſweet Saviour</l>
               <l>Indur'd a worſer ſhow'r;</l>
               <l>For me he cry'd,</l>
               <l>For me he dy'd.</l>
               <l>Therefore in Pain let me not think amiſs;</l>
               <l>For all my Pains are not like one of his.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <head>Content.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>I Smile to hear my friends ask why I keep</l>
               <l>A TAVERN, and thereby to break my ſleep.</l>
               <l>Epaminondas was a Generall,</l>
               <l>After a private Captain; yet no fall</l>
               <l>Did he account it: And doe I not well,</l>
               <l>To keep an Inn, think it an Hermit's Cell?</l>
               <l>S. Paul's reſolve I can't but well reſent,</l>
               <l>I've learn'd in each eſtate to be content;</l>
               <l>And my Ambition is to keep a TAVERN,</l>
               <l>To know how well I ſuch a place can govern.</l>
               <l>In patience to poſſeſs my ſoul, I crave;</l>
               <l>And what I ask in ſaith, Lord, I ſhall have.</l>
               <l>I am a Merchant ſtill; yet doe not ſtart</l>
               <l>From ſelling French, and Spaniſh Wine by th'Quart.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Of Zeno I have read in purples dealing,</l>
               <l>Impoveriſh'd upon the ſalt-ſeas failing;</l>
               <l>Yet ſaying this, although his 'ſtate half crack'd,</l>
               <l>I ſayled beſt when as I was ſhipwrack'd.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Brave was his reſolution, who did lie</l>
               <l>His two laſt years torn by the Strangury.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:104586:33"/>Had liv'd his middle age moſt proſp'rouſly,</l>
               <l>Who in the midſt of torments thus could ſay;</l>
               <l>Oh my Lord God, how gracious haſt thou been!</l>
               <l>Forty eight years of health, but two of pain:</l>
               <l>Bleſt be thy name for th'mercy in forbearing,</l>
               <l>And for thy Juſtice, Lord, in me afflicting.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>I can't but ſcorn and pity great Auguſtus,</l>
               <l>Who ſo betrayed humane frailty thus;</l>
               <l>After th'defeat of ſome choice Troops, he fals,</l>
               <l>And frantick-like knocks his head 'gainſt the wals,</l>
               <l>Utt'ring unmanlike Exclamations,</l>
               <l>Varus reſtore me my loſt Legions!</l>
               <l>When we are miſerable, oh our tempers!</l>
               <l>Then we doe adde unto it by diſtempers.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>I ſee the Indian now Husbanding</l>
               <l>One Tree, and t'all his houſhold uſes bring,</l>
               <l>Timber, Thatch, Meat, Oil, Honey, Medicine,</l>
               <l>Sauce, Drink, Utenſils, Ships, Cables, Sails, Wine;</l>
               <l>And tell me, pray you, what is it that frets</l>
               <l>The pleaſant ſpirit of Anachorets?</l>
               <l>Says the Apoſtle, having food and rayment,</l>
               <l>Oh let us learn to be therewith content!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>No murmuring for guilty ſubornations;</l>
               <l>For here's no cauſe in theſe our meaner ſtations.</l>
               <l>No checks for ſecret, vile contrivances</l>
               <l>Of publick, high-handed great villanies.</l>
               <l>Great men in Great bottoms ſayl in the deep,</l>
               <l>Poor men in Barks ſtill near the ſhore doe creep;</l>
               <l>And I have ſeen the ſmall one gain the Creek,</l>
               <l>When th'great one, (God thou knowſt) was oft to ſeek!</l>
               <l>I am not troubled here with Titius vulture:</l>
               <l>Though my Eſtate is ſmall, my ſtate is ſure.</l>
               <l>Here (Aethiopian-like) with my door open</l>
               <l>I ſleep, while people doe both goe and come.</l>
               <l>What Lucius wrote, I doe affirm no leſs,</l>
               <l>That one houres miſchief drowns the great'ſt exceſs.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>My Caſe was worſe, when I was in reſtraint;</l>
               <l>And yet that hath been th'caſe of many a Saint.</l>
               <l>My Caſe was worſe, when vulture-Povetry</l>
               <l>Did gnaw my minde, and I no meat could come by.</l>
               <l>I wi'nt repine, becauſe my miſery</l>
               <l>Is laid upon me, Lord, ſo fav'rably;</l>
               <l>And I will be content upon this ground,</l>
               <l>I ſhall not want, if'ts better to abound:</l>
               <l>Nay, I doe beg, O Lord, (with holy fear)</l>
               <l>Not to be ſo curs'd, to be happy here.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:104586:34"/>With David, Lord, I doe deſire to ſing,</l>
               <l>The Lord my Shephard is, I lack no thing.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>En hour content ſé dit.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <head>The Opinion, ſent to Sir <hi>R.S.</hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <l>MY firm Opinion, dear Sir, is this,</l>
               <l>And God inform me, (if I be amiſs!)</l>
               <l>Or ſhall I boldly ſpeak with leave, and fear not</l>
               <l>What fond Religion my Tenents are not.</l>
               <l>Kinde Familiſts, or wider Libertines,</l>
               <l>Eraſtians, Anti-trinitarians,</l>
               <l>Croſs Anabaptiſts, bold Arminians,</l>
               <l>Conceited, fond Manifeſtarians;</l>
               <l>Fierce Millenaries, Antinomians,</l>
               <l>Socinians, condemned Arians,</l>
               <l>Curſed, abhorred Anti-ſcripturiſts,</l>
               <l>Giddy Browniſts, conceited Perfectiſts,</l>
               <l>Mortalians, Enthuſiaſts ſo ſtrange,</l>
               <l>And Seekers through forbidden things that range,</l>
               <l>And ſuch like, I deteſt, don't underſtand,</l>
               <l>Only beleeving what my God command;</l>
               <l>Fear God, and love my Neighbor, Chriſtian love,</l>
               <l>Is the true badg of our Maſter above:</l>
               <l>Yet from them we may learn; for from a Turk,</l>
               <l>A thing I read of makes my bowels work;</l>
               <l>An Engliſhman in his unwiſer rage</l>
               <l>Did ſtrike a Turk his guide; yet on the ſtage</l>
               <l>Ne'r came his paſſion: for's villany</l>
               <l>Shall I neglect my duty? no ſaith he;</l>
               <l>Nor I neglect to own my prov'd Religion,</l>
               <l>Although I doe incur the Sects deriſion;</l>
               <l>On truth of Scriptures are my tenents grounded,</l>
               <l>Which would make Atheiſts Chriſtians, if well ſounded.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="1">
               <head>1.</head>
               <l>Had it not been the Word of God alone,</l>
               <l>The falſhood had detected been, and ſhown.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="2">
               <head>2.</head>
               <l>And for the Penmen of the Scripture, ſee!</l>
               <l>They ſet not forth their own nobility,</l>
               <l>Glory, or Vertue, but with one conſent,</l>
               <l>Declar'd the will of him that had them ſent:</l>
               <l>Yea, faults diſgraceful to themſelves, and thoſe</l>
               <l>Their iſſues they did true-free-ly diſcloſe;</l>
               <l>A proof that nat'rall Reaſon did not boaſt;</l>
               <l>But meerly guided by the holy Ghoſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="3">
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:104586:34"/>
               <head>3.</head>
               <l>Thirdly, the ſtile is writ plain, and ſimply;</l>
               <l>Yet full of purer grace, and majeſty;</l>
               <l>For it doth curb the proud, exalt the meek,</l>
               <l>And offer Chriſt to thoſe that do him ſeek.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="4">
               <head>4.</head>
               <l>The Scripture is an hiſtory ſo old,</l>
               <l>Four thouſand years before Chriſts birth was told,</l>
               <l>Old Authours do accord with Scripture ſo,</l>
               <l>As that part which in Hiſtory doth go,</l>
               <l>And miracles confirm it, The Sun ſtands,</l>
               <l>The dead are rais'd, and nothing it withſtands.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="5">
               <head>5.</head>
               <l>The record of the ſpirit which who reſents,</l>
               <l>Is argument againſt all arguments,</l>
               <l>And becauſe likely you may it reſent,</l>
               <l>I've plac'd<note n="*" place="margin">Joh. 7.17 one way, and Matt. 7.7, 8. Luk. 11.13 and James 1.7.</note> quotations that are pertinent;</l>
               <l>But if y' expect me t' anſwer all objections,</l>
               <l>I don't intend to make ſuch larger Sections;</l>
               <l>Yet ſince the Scripture is God's written Word,</l>
               <l>I chooſe that true Religion it afford.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>I would improve the duty in the Law,</l>
               <l>And Goſpel-promiſe both imbrace, and aw,</l>
               <l>The one a ſpur for holineſs to fit;</l>
               <l>Th' other to unbelief a curb, or bit.</l>
               <l>Out of the ſenſe of my neceſſity,</l>
               <l>In higheſt manner grace to magnifie;</l>
               <l>Yet to avoid wilde Antinomianiſm,</l>
               <l>And on the other ſide t' avoid the Schiſm</l>
               <l>Of Phariſaical Po'pry; neverth'leſs</l>
               <l>Mortification, and holineſs,</l>
               <l>To doth both punctually, and exact,</l>
               <l>And indeed here's the right ſenſe, and the act.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Working ſalvation with fear and trembling,</l>
               <l>As if there were no grace to juſtifie,</l>
               <l>And yet ſo firmly reſting and believing,</l>
               <l>As if no good thing had been done us by.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Sim.</hi> As theſe our bodies live by earthly food,</l>
               <l>So true Religion doth our ſouls moſt good.</l>
               <l>As Earth is ſoftened by Iron us'd with art,</l>
               <l>So doth Religion temper th' hardeſt heart:</l>
               <l>Yet as ſore eyes can't gaze againſt the Sun,</l>
               <l>So wicked mindes brook not Religion.</l>
               <l>As Med'cines makes ſick bodies whole and ſound,</l>
               <l>So doth Religion waſh out Errours wound.</l>
               <l>Like as a torch us in the dark directs,</l>
               <l>So doth Religion guide from wand'ring Sects.</l>
               <l>As want of food the body ſterve, and ſcant,</l>
               <l>So pines the the Soul through pure Religions want.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="46" facs="tcp:104586:35"/>
                  <hi>Examp.</hi> Brennus for wronging of Religion</l>
               <l>Was ſmitten with a thunder bolt from Heav'n.</l>
               <l>The chiefeſt Oath th' Athenians had was this,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Pugnabo pro ſacris, &amp; cum aliis, &amp; ſolus,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Pherecydes Religion nick-nam'd;</l>
               <l>For which he was by worms alive conſum'd.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Methinks I hear you ask what Regiment</l>
               <l>I vote within the Church, ſith detriment</l>
               <l>Came by the Biſhops lordings. Then I ſay,</l>
               <l>Biſhops that do both watch their flock, and pray;</l>
               <l>It was the Judgement of that learned King,</l>
               <l>Which I here quote, ſith he did Scripture bring</l>
               <l>To prove his Tenet. Only this indent,</l>
               <l>Civill affaires out of his element,</l>
               <l>As it was ſay'd of Andrews, and a Church</l>
               <l>Kept in his houſe. I hope none lie at lurch,</l>
               <l>Here need's n' Oedipus. Then for the rule of ſtate</l>
               <l>If God ſhall pleaſe! that way that was of late,</l>
               <l>But howſoe'r, (as the' Shepheard ſai'd o'th Weather,)</l>
               <l>I this my ſtrange, yet good opinion gather,</l>
               <l>That there ſhall be ſuch times, as I pleaſe, ſee!</l>
               <l>Such as pleaſe God ſhall pleaſing be to me.</l>
               <l>This is m'opinion (dear Sir) and why</l>
               <l>Should I be guilty of a needles ly?</l>
               <l>For Herbert ſaith, nothing doth need a lye,</l>
               <l>A fault that want's it moſt, grow's worſe thereby;</l>
               <l>Then (Sir) ſith yon do know my'pinion weak,</l>
               <l>If I re-viſit you, vouchſafe to ſpeak.</l>
               <l>But pray do not ſo groſly me miſtake,</l>
               <l>As to think all was Goſpell that I ſpake,</l>
               <l>For as Baſil gravil'd Eunomius</l>
               <l>The Heretick (pretending boldly thus,</l>
               <l>That he knew God's divinity, apart)</l>
               <l>With one, and twenty queſtious of an Art;</l>
               <l>So you may me in twenty queſtions more,</l>
               <l>And you may well judge me fooliſh therefore,</l>
               <l>But I take liberty of Conſcience</l>
               <l>Here to declare of truth the naked ſence,</l>
               <l>And am grown proud, ſith you do not refuſe</l>
               <l>To honour with acceptance the dul muſe, of ſir your ſervant</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>N. M.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <head>Lords DAY.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>THis holy day,</l>
               <l>(Which Heav'n diſplay,)</l>
               <l>I do adore,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:104586:35"/>Five thouſand years,</l>
               <l>(Free from all fears)</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Sabbath's</hi> name bore.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Now ſixteen hundred,</l>
               <l>('Tis to be wondred)</l>
               <l>Called <hi>Lords-day.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>By't to ſerve thee,</l>
               <l>'Twas made we ſee,</l>
               <l>Not for to play.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Each ſeaventh thought,</l>
               <l>Should thee be brought,</l>
               <l>For they're thy due;</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But thy ſeventh day,</l>
               <l>Half's caſt away;</l>
               <l>Oh 'tis too true!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Yet I'll thee ſeek,</l>
               <l>(Who art ſo meek)</l>
               <l>Of th' week each day;</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>For thy mercies,</l>
               <l>Juſtice likewiſe,</l>
               <l>I'll <hi>praiſe or pray.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <head>THE SINNER. The Argument.</head>
            <argument>
               <l>While Ioab doth beſiege warlick Rabbah,</l>
               <l>David doe's adultery with Bathsheba,</l>
               <l>Send's for Vriah for to cover it,</l>
               <l>But he'd not home, nor drunk, nor ſober yet;</l>
               <l>He carrie'th Ioab th' letter of his death,</l>
               <l>Ioab the newes to David then ſendeth,</l>
               <l>And David Bathſheba dow marrieth.</l>
            </argument>
            <div type="section">
               <head>SECT.</head>
               <l>IT came to paſſe after the year expir'd</l>
               <l>The time that Kings go forth to battle 'tir'd</l>
               <l>In Warre-preſaging ſteel; David commands</l>
               <l>His Gen'rall Joab with his warlike hands</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="48" facs="tcp:104586:36"/>Extracted out all Iſrael, and they ſtroyed,</l>
               <l>The Ammonitiſh children, Rabbah beſieg'd;</l>
               <l>But David at Jerus'lem tarried,</l>
               <l>And 't came to paſs in a cool ev'ning tide,</l>
               <l>That David roſe from off his bed, and walked</l>
               <l>Upon the roof of the Kings houſe, thus talked</l>
               <l>His eyes unto his luſt, that bathing woman</l>
               <l>Ir very beautifull to look upon;</l>
               <l>And he ſent, and inquired of the woman;</l>
               <l>Is't not Bathſheba, daughter of Elan</l>
               <l>Saith one, wife of Uriah the Hittite?</l>
               <l>And David ſent, and took her for a night,</l>
               <l>And ſhe came in to him, and he lay with her;</l>
               <l>(For her uncleanneſs was taken from off her;)</l>
               <l>And ſhe returned to her houſe, conceived,</l>
               <l>And ſent, and told, I am with childe by David,</l>
               <l>And David ſent to Joab, ſend Uriah.</l>
               <l>And Joab ſent to David wrong'd Uriah,</l>
               <l>David demands of him how Joab did,</l>
               <l>How th' people, and how the War proſpered?</l>
               <l>And bid him go to 's houſe, and waſh his feet,</l>
               <l>And after him he ſent a meſs of meat;</l>
               <l>But Uriah ſlept at th' Kings houſe door,</l>
               <l>Not going to his own; but choſe the floor,</l>
               <l>And when they David told of it, he ſaid,</l>
               <l>Cam'ſt thou not from th' journey? why haſt not laid</l>
               <l>At thine own houſe? And Uriah reply'd</l>
               <l>Th' Ark, Iſrael, Judah in tents abide,</l>
               <l>And my Lord Joab, and his ſervants all,</l>
               <l>(And am I better than my General?)</l>
               <l>In open field incamped are, ſhall I</l>
               <l>Then to my houſe to eat, drink, and to lie</l>
               <l>By my Wife's ſide? as thou liveſt, O King,</l>
               <l>And as thy ſoul, I will not do this thing.</l>
               <l>And David ſaid, tarry here this day, and th' morrow.</l>
               <l>And thou ſhalt go; ſo he ſtay'd there with ſorrow,</l>
               <l>And when David had called him, he drank,</l>
               <l>And ate before him, and he made him drunk;</l>
               <l>And at Even, according to his uſe,</l>
               <l>He lay with' ſervants, went not to his houſe.</l>
               <l>And 't came to paſs ith' morning, that David</l>
               <l>A letter by Uriah poor had writ,</l>
               <l>Unto Joab, ſaying ith' main battel</l>
               <l>Appoint Uriah, and retreat untill</l>
               <l>He ſmitten is, and die; and Joab did</l>
               <l>Accordingly (in which he much miſ-did.)</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:104586:36"/>And by a meſſenger he certifi'd</l>
               <l>How good Uriah valiantly dy'd,</l>
               <l>And when his wife had heard that he was dead,</l>
               <l>For him, (as ſhe had cauſe) ſhe then mourned,</l>
               <l>And when that Tempus luctus was ore-paſt,</l>
               <l>David ſent, and fet her to 's houſe in haſte,</l>
               <l>And ſhe his ſcarcely lawfull wife became,</l>
               <l>And bare by him, and unto him a ſon;</l>
               <l>But this thing of David's hot luſtfull love</l>
               <l>Diſpleaſed God, that ſits, and ſees above.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>MEDITATION.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>NOthing can ſhew David like as himſelf;</l>
                  <l>His Poeſie 's a ſhip, ours but a ſhelf.</l>
                  <l>Whoſe ſin forgiven is, is moſt bleſſed,</l>
                  <l>And bleſſed he, whoſe ſin is covered.</l>
                  <l>Bleſſed is the man unto whom the Lord</l>
                  <l>Imputeth not iniquity; O God!</l>
                  <l>And in whoſe ſpirit there is no guile. When I</l>
                  <l>Kept ſilence my bones waxed old, and dry,</l>
                  <l>Through my roaring all the day long, alas!</l>
                  <l>For day, night, thy hand on me heavy was:</l>
                  <l>My moiſture unto Summers drought is turned:</l>
                  <l>My ſin unto thee I acknowledged,</l>
                  <l>And mine iniquity I have not hid:</l>
                  <l>I ſaid, t' confeſs my ſins I will begin,</l>
                  <l>And thou forgaveſt the guilt of my ſin.</l>
                  <l>Thus David could in former time confeſs,</l>
                  <l>And beg for pardon for his wickedneſs;</l>
                  <l>But he that was foretime Gods Champion brave,</l>
                  <l>Left but unto himſelf is now a ſlave</l>
                  <l>Unto his luſt, his luſt, his luſt, his luſt,</l>
                  <l>For which moſt bitter waters taſte he muſt.</l>
                  <l>Here may we learn occaſion to fly</l>
                  <l>That ſoul-confounding, foul iniquity.</l>
                  <l>Here may we ſee the tricks we have to ſin,</l>
                  <l>And how our ſelves we do beleaguer in,</l>
                  <l>To hug our Cockatricial luſts, which will</l>
                  <l>With their infectious breaths our poor ſouls kill.</l>
                  <l>I am with childe to meditate of all</l>
                  <l>The accidents in this our David's fall;</l>
                  <l>Sampſon by beauty was ſurprized, and</l>
                  <l>Who have obeyed not Beauty's command?</l>
                  <l>Victorious Hercules, mighty, and ſweet,</l>
                  <l>Laid down his courage at fair Beauty's feet;</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="50" facs="tcp:104586:37"/>The Lybian lions (they ſay) loſe their might,</l>
                  <l>If on a Beauty once they ſet their ſight.</l>
                  <l>Zeno the prince of Stoicks did agree</l>
                  <l>That Beauty's like could very hardly be:</l>
                  <l>But grant that Nature Beauty thus gave place;</l>
                  <l>How cam't that Beauty conquer'd David's Grace?</l>
                  <l>If Fleſh ſubmitted unto Beauty's lure,</l>
                  <l>Oh! how could Spirit ſervitude endure!</l>
                  <l>Oh! then, my ſoul, learn thou here to repent,</l>
                  <l>And God-diſpleaſing ſins be ſure relent</l>
                  <l>At thy firſt ſinning: and, Oh God above,</l>
                  <l>Guide my ſoul always by that holy Dove;</l>
                  <l>And let thy deputy within my ſoul,</l>
                  <l>Great Conſcience, my ſmalleſt ſins controul:</l>
                  <l>And let me weep, and meditate, and weep,</l>
                  <l>And pray thee that from ſuch ſins thou me keep.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Had David been in Joab's place, no doubt</l>
                  <l>His lazie luſt had then receiv'd a rout:</l>
                  <l>Had Grace in Joab Gen'ral been, I ſay,</l>
                  <l>He'd not ſo priz'd that darling of one day,</l>
                  <l>That bubble Honour, and had not made guilty</l>
                  <l>His King with murtherous adultery.</l>
                  <l>Good David fallen into ſuch a ſin!</l>
                  <l>Thus do we ſee that dangerous Beauty's gin.</l>
                  <l>Eve's whining voice loſt Adam's paradice,</l>
                  <l>And Bathſheba's fair looks caus'd David's vice.</l>
                  <l>Juſtly lamented David, now I ſee</l>
                  <l>The power of ſoothing Proſperity:</l>
                  <l>We heard not of thy cauſing Drunkenneſs,</l>
                  <l>When God thee with Adverſity did bleſs.</l>
                  <l>Nothing but ſing and weep, and weep and ſing,</l>
                  <l>God's Word unto our liſtning ears did bring.</l>
                  <l>Obedient Son, good Shepherd, loving Father,</l>
                  <l>Careful Servant, ſtout Captain; (yet not ſmother</l>
                  <l>God's praiſes to augment thine own:) Muſick</l>
                  <l>Came from thy skilful hand to the brain-ſick;</l>
                  <l>In all thine Offices renouncing man</l>
                  <l>More then the falſly-ſtyl'd Capuchian.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>By this I know the Scripture to be right,</l>
                  <l>Sith David here confeſs'd in the world's ſight,</l>
                  <l>A ſin to him diſgraceful: he did write,</l>
                  <l>But th'holy Ghoſt unto him did indite.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>We muſt make haſte that David may repent;</l>
                  <l>In which ſure none will think the time miſ-ſpent.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="51" facs="tcp:104586:37"/>
            <head>The REPENTANT. <hi>The Argument.</hi>
            </head>
            <argument>
               <l>Nathan's quaint parable of the Ewe-lamb</l>
               <l>makes David judge himſelf to be in blame.</l>
               <l>David by Nathan's words being reproved,</l>
               <l>confeſſeth his ſin, and is pardoned.</l>
               <l>David mourns and prays for the childe in breath;</l>
               <l>Solomon's born, and nam'd Jedidiah.</l>
               <l>David taketh Rabbah, (Uriah's death)</l>
               <l>and the people thereof he tortureth.</l>
            </argument>
            <div type="section">
               <head>SECT.</head>
               <l>ANd the Lord ſent Nathan unto David laid<note place="margin">2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 12.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Sleeping in ſin, and unto him he ſaid;</l>
               <l>There were two men in one City: pure need</l>
               <l>Oppreſt the one, the other did exceed</l>
               <l>In flocks and herds; but the poor man had nought</l>
               <l>Save onely one little ewe-lamb, which he had bought</l>
               <l>And nouriſhed, and it grew up together</l>
               <l>With him and with his children; and the weather</l>
               <l>Did ſcarce afflict it; of his meat it fed,</l>
               <l>And drank of his own cup; in's boſome-bed</l>
               <l>It lay, and was unto him as a daughter:</l>
               <l>And the rich man put it unto the ſlaughter,</l>
               <l>Having a traveller coming to's boord,</l>
               <l>And of his coin to take could not afford,</l>
               <l>Of his own flock or herd to dreſs; yet can</l>
               <l>Take th' poor man's lamb for that way-faring man,</l>
               <l>And dreſſed it. And David's anger was</l>
               <l>Greatly kindled againſt the man: alas!</l>
               <l>He thought not of himſelf; for then ſurely</l>
               <l>He'd not have ſaid, The man ſhall ſurely die</l>
               <l>That did this thing, and had no pitie. Then</l>
               <l>Nathan ſaid to David, Thou art the man.</l>
               <l>Thus ſaith the God of Iſrael, I, I</l>
               <l>Anointed thee King with a hand moſt high;</l>
               <l>And out of Saul's hand did deliver thee;</l>
               <l>Thy maſter's houſe eke I did give to thee:</l>
               <l>Thy maſter's wives into thy boſome fell;</l>
               <l>I gave thee Judah, and mine Iſrael.</l>
               <l>And if theſe were too little in thine eye,</l>
               <l>I would have giv'n thee greater dignity, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="52" facs="tcp:104586:38"/>Wherefore haſt thou deſpis'd God's great command</l>
               <l>To do evil in his ſight with a hand</l>
               <l>So high? thou haſt killed Uriah poor</l>
               <l>With ſword, and made the Hittite's Wife a whore,</l>
               <l>And taken his Wife to be thy Wife,</l>
               <l>And by Ammon haſt taken away his life.</l>
               <l>Now therefore the ſword ſhall never depart</l>
               <l>Thine houſe, ſince thou, deſpiſed me in heart,</l>
               <l>And ta'en Uriahs Wife to be thy Wife,</l>
               <l>Thus ſaith the Lord, behold, I will make ſtrife,</l>
               <l>And evil againſt thee out of thine houſe,</l>
               <l>And I will take thy wife before thine eyes,</l>
               <l>And give thy neighbour them, and he ſhall lie</l>
               <l>In the ſight of the Sun thy choice Wives by:</l>
               <l>For thou didſt ſecretly; but I will do</l>
               <l>This thing 'fore Iſrael, and the Suns ſight too:</l>
               <l>And David ſaid unto Nathan, I have</l>
               <l>Sinned, I have ſinned, ſinned I have.</l>
               <l>And Nathan ſaid to David certainly,</l>
               <l>Thy ſin is put away, thou ſhalt not die,</l>
               <l>Howbeit becauſe thou haſt by this deed given</l>
               <l>Occaſion that the great God of heaven</l>
               <l>Men ſpeak of may blaſphemouſly,</l>
               <l>The childe born unto thee ſhall ſurely die.</l>
               <l>And Nathan went unto his houſe and th' Lord</l>
               <l>Stroke Davids childe by Uriahs wife with's rod,</l>
               <l>And it was very ſick, David therefore</l>
               <l>Beſought God for the childe, and did implore</l>
               <l>The Almighty by faſting, and he went in,</l>
               <l>And lay all night upon the earth for 's ſin.</l>
               <l>And th' Elders of his houſe aroſe and would</l>
               <l>Him raiſed have from off the earth's cold mould;</l>
               <l>But he would not, neither did he eat bread:</l>
               <l>And on the ſeventh day the childe was dead,</l>
               <l>And Davids ſervants fear'd to tell him ſo.</l>
               <l>For they ſaid, when the childe was alive, lo,</l>
               <l>We ſpake unto him, and he would not hear;</l>
               <l>How will he vex, if this arive his ear?</l>
               <l>But when David ſaw that the ſervants whiſpered,</l>
               <l>David perceived that the childe was dead.</l>
               <l>David ſaid to 's ſervants, Is the childe dead?</l>
               <l>And they ſaid tremblingly, the childe is dead:</l>
               <l>Then David roſe from off the earth and waſhed,</l>
               <l>'Nointed himſelf, and his apparel changed,</l>
               <l>And came to the Lords houſe and worſhipped.</l>
               <l>Then he came to his own, and he required</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="53" facs="tcp:104586:38"/>Them to ſet bread before him, and he eat,</l>
               <l>Then ſaid his ſervants unto him hereat,</l>
               <l>We wonder thou didſt faſt and weep for th' childe</l>
               <l>Alive, but dead thy ſorrow is exil'd;</l>
               <l>And he ſaid, while the childe was yet alive</l>
               <l>I wept and faſted, God may lend it life,</l>
               <l>And be gracious to me, ſaid I; now 'tis paſt,</l>
               <l>He being dead, wherefore ſhould I refaſt?</l>
               <l>Can I bring him here back again? 'twill be</l>
               <l>That I ſhall go to him, he not return to me:</l>
               <l>And David comforted his Bathſheba,</l>
               <l>And he went in, and with her he did lay;</l>
               <l>She bare a ſon and call'd 's name Solomon,</l>
               <l>And the Lord loved him, and Nathan's word</l>
               <l>Nam'd Jedidiah, becauſe of the Lord.</l>
               <l>And Joab fought againſt Rabbah, took the City.</l>
               <l>And he ſent David word, (a pleaſant ditty)</l>
               <l>Now therefore come with 'reſt of Iſrael,</l>
               <l>Encamp and take the City, leaſt they tell,</l>
               <l>'Tis Joabs City; ſo the King came down,</l>
               <l>And fought and took the City, and the Crown</l>
               <l>Of their Kings head, great was the Cities ſpoil;</l>
               <l>He put them under ſaws and harrows vile,</l>
               <l>And all their Cities to the vexation;</l>
               <l>Then he return'd, and I to meditation.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>MEDITATION.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>HEre may we ſee good Nathan's holy fraud,</l>
                  <l>Yet he knew well, David muſt not be claw'd,</l>
                  <l>At ſuch a time, for he ſaith, thou 'rt the man</l>
                  <l>O let truths Champions charge in the van,</l>
                  <l>All ſinners thus, and let the ſinners fall</l>
                  <l>From ſin and riſe in faith in general,</l>
                  <l>Not blaming holy Nathans who do ſtrive</l>
                  <l>To marry us to Chriſt, from the world un-wive:</l>
                  <l>A ſtranger came to David, 'twas a ſtranger</l>
                  <l>Indeed to him, but in the world a Ranger.</l>
                  <l>For this his ſin, that would ſorrow the ſtones,</l>
                  <l>Me thinks I hear good David's ſighs and groans.</l>
                  <l>Saying, ye gate unto iniquity,</l>
                  <l>My un-reſtrained luſt and liberty;</l>
                  <l>By this my foul abhord adultery,</l>
                  <l>To nature I have done an injury,</l>
                  <l>But to the God of Nature more. O ſin!</l>
                  <l>By thee my ſorrow doth but now begin.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="54" facs="tcp:104586:39"/>Sin! ſin! ſin! ſin! a worſe then thee can't be;</l>
                  <l>For here had been no evil but for thee.</l>
                  <l>Oh grief beyond tongue-eloquence! whoſe ſmart</l>
                  <l>Is onely truely known within my heart.</l>
                  <l>My ſoul, my ſoul receiveth violence</l>
                  <l>By this my beaſtly baſe concupiſcence.</l>
                  <l>Nay, how know I, but by continuance,</l>
                  <l>My luſt may grow to damned impudence?</l>
                  <l>Oh in my ſoul I have a gnawing ſence!</l>
                  <l>Greatneſs doth make it great incontinence.</l>
                  <l>How will the Wicked now rejoyce and ſay</l>
                  <l>With ſcorn, See how the Saint is faln away!</l>
                  <l>What wrong ſhall I do to thy Church, O Lord,</l>
                  <l>Unto this holy, holy, holy Word!</l>
                  <l>My owl-ſight eyes were dazled with her light,</l>
                  <l>Yet ſaw too clearly in that darker night.</l>
                  <l>Oh that I had not up my roof ſo gone!</l>
                  <l>Or that I there, there, there had been alone!</l>
                  <l>That that too nimble tongue had not me told</l>
                  <l>What th'woman was; for that made luſt ſo bold.</l>
                  <l>What did I wiſh t'have been alone? Unwiſe;</l>
                  <l>That cauſed me to be tyrant luſt's priſe:</l>
                  <l>For had my God been with me, I had not</l>
                  <l>Been ſuch a wretched, fooliſh, ſinful ſot.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>If for adultery my ſoul thus finde</l>
                  <l>To grieve, What ſhall ſhe do for that behinde,</l>
                  <l>Abhorred murther? Now my ſoul falls down,</l>
                  <l>And's truely dead <hi>(pro tempore)</hi> in a ſwoon.</l>
                  <l>Oh lend thy mercy, Lord, Oh Lord ſupport</l>
                  <l>My failing heart, that I may thus report</l>
                  <l>To all ſucceeding ages. Oh my God!</l>
                  <l>Let th' holy Spirit have again abode</l>
                  <l>Within my heart; and pardon all my ſins,</l>
                  <l>And eke prevent Satan's inchanting gins.</l>
                  <l>Dread Majeſtie! Oh let thy mercy ſhine</l>
                  <l>Upon my darkned ſoul: let light divine</l>
                  <l>Deſcend into it, that by that clear light,</l>
                  <l>I may of thy paths have a certain ſight.</l>
                  <l>But teach me to repent, and that's as good</l>
                  <l>As if th'hadſt ſeal'd my pardon with thy blood.</l>
                  <l>I'll let him ſpeak himſelf. A hand or eye</l>
                  <l>"By Hilyard drawn, is worth an Hiſtory</l>
                  <l>"By a worſe Painter made, ſaith learned Donne:</l>
                  <l>Therefore hear David's verſe; for I have done.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="55" facs="tcp:104586:39"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Verſe</hi> 1. <hi>PSALM</hi> 51.</head>
            <l n="1">1. HAve mercy upon me, O gracious God,</l>
            <l>According to thy loving kindneſs Lord,</l>
            <l>According to thy mercies multitude,</l>
            <l>Blot out my hainous ſins which did intrude.</l>
            <l n="2">2 Waſh me throughly from mine iniquity,</l>
            <l>and cleanſe me from my great impiety.</l>
            <l n="3">3 For I acknowledge my ſins, and they be</l>
            <l>before my weeping eyes continually.</l>
            <l n="4">4 'Gainſt thee, thee onely have I ſinned, and</l>
            <l>done this in thy ſight with ſo high a hand,</l>
            <l>That thou mightſt be juſtified when thou ſpeakeſt,</l>
            <l>and be alwayes moſt clear when thou judgeſt.</l>
            <l n="5">5 Lo I was ſhapen in iniquity,</l>
            <l>and in vile ſin did my mother conceive me!</l>
            <l n="6">6 Lo thou deſir'ſt truth in the inward part,</l>
            <l>and thou ſhalt teach me wiſdom in my heart.</l>
            <l n="7">7 Purge me with hyſſop, I ſhall be clean ſo,</l>
            <l>waſh me and I ſhall be whiter than ſnow.</l>
            <l n="8">8 Make me to hear ſweet joy and gladneſs voice,</l>
            <l>that the bones which thou haſt broke may rejoyce.</l>
            <l n="9">9 From my ſin Lord hide thine all-ſeeing eyes,</l>
            <l>and blot out all my great iniquities.</l>
            <l n="10">10 Create in me a clean heart, O my God,</l>
            <l>and conſtant ſpirit give in me abode!</l>
            <l n="11">11 O caſt me not from out thy bleſſed preſence,</l>
            <l>take not from me thy holy Spirits ſenſe!</l>
            <l n="12">12 Reſtore to me the joy of thy ſalvation,</l>
            <l>and uphold me with thy free Spirits motion.</l>
            <l n="13">13 Then will I teach tranſgreſſours great thy wayes,</l>
            <l>and ſinners ſhall convert by me thy ſayes.</l>
            <l n="14">14 O free me from bloud-guiltineſs, O Lord!</l>
            <l>thou God of my ſalvation it afford.</l>
            <l n="15">15 My tongue ſhall ſing thy Righteouſneſs, O God,</l>
            <l>Lord open thou my Lips, and them upraiſe,</l>
            <l>then ſhall my mouth ſhew forth thy louder praiſe.</l>
            <l n="16">16 For thou deſir'ſt no ſacrifice, Ide bring</l>
            <l>it elſe; thou delight'ſt not in burnt-offering.</l>
            <l n="17">17 Thy ſacrifices are a broken ſpirit,</l>
            <l>a broken contrite heart is thy beſt merit.</l>
            <l n="18">18 Do good in thy good pleaſure unto Sion,</l>
            <l>build thou the wals of thy Jeruſalem.</l>
            <l n="19">19 Then ſhalt thou pleaſed be with ſacrifice</l>
            <l>of our lame, haſting, but half Righteouſneſs;</l>
            <l>with burnt-offering, and whole burnt-offering,</l>
            <l>then ſhall they bullocks to thine altar bring.</l>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="56" facs="tcp:104586:40"/>
            <head>MEDITATION.</head>
            <l>HEre is a Leſſon of concernment here,</l>
            <l>A Davids Leſſon, which may ſeem a meer</l>
            <l>Folly to fooliſh folk. What mourn ſo much,</l>
            <l>For a then living childe, and yet to grutch,</l>
            <l>After 'twas dead? O here's a work of Grace</l>
            <l>Which now repenting David doth imbrace!</l>
            <l>He'd prayed for its life in either World;</l>
            <l>And ſince God's juſt deſerv'd anger hurl'd</l>
            <l>The Babe from mourning David, David is</l>
            <l>Inform'd by faith that it its makers is,</l>
            <l>And he therein afflicted for his ſin,</l>
            <l>Which he deſires to be contented in.</l>
            <l>He throws not Cities down as Alexander,</l>
            <l>At his friends death, nor let their paſſion wander.</l>
            <l>He's not ſo frantick in his vain laments,</l>
            <l>When his childe travelling removes his tents,</l>
            <l>As to demoliſh the Palace where it died,</l>
            <l>As one of our Kings did (if not belied)</l>
            <l>Heathens can learn men better Leſſons; Fie,</l>
            <l>Will men th' Eternal great Decree deny?</l>
            <l>Hector to's wife Andromache ſaid why</l>
            <l>Do you grieve my death? all men are born to die.</l>
            <l>Gorgias ask't in's ſickneſs, how he fareth,</l>
            <l>Saith, ſleep now yields me to his brother death.</l>
            <l>But to our Theme. David now confeſſeth.</l>
            <l>His deareſt Bathſheba, whoſe ſweet childes death</l>
            <l>Hath over-whelmed her heart with ſorrow; yet</l>
            <l>She now conſiders it was Natures debt,</l>
            <l>And 'tis meer curteſie if we are ſpar'd</l>
            <l>To ſeventy years, for death is not debard</l>
            <l>From ſhooting us any time if God</l>
            <l>His nimble feet with a command hath ſhod.</l>
            <l>So David went in and did lie with her,</l>
            <l>And ſhe did bear a ſon, which ſon did bear</l>
            <l>An Emblem of God's love even in his Name.</l>
            <l>By God by Nathan given; for Solomon</l>
            <l>Is Jedidiah called, 'cauſe of the Lord.</l>
            <l>And Joab had fought Rabbah with the ſword,</l>
            <l>And he ſent for David, ſaying, come thou</l>
            <l>With the reſt of the people, or I vow,</l>
            <l>The City will by my name called be,</l>
            <l>Which I confeſs our King, belongs to thee.</l>
            <l>Here was right Captain General, for lo,</l>
            <l>He knew how to intitle David to</l>
            <l>
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:104586:40"/>The honour of the action; faithfull man,</l>
            <l>In this matter (I pray) who blame thee can?</l>
            <l>So David marched to the town and took</l>
            <l>What ever the conquered people look</l>
            <l>Upon as once was theirs; their Kings rich Crown</l>
            <l>From off their Kings head, and ſet on his own.</l>
            <l>Thus do I ſee that that old phraſe doth hit,</l>
            <l>Fortior qui ſe, quàm qui fortiſſima vincit.</l>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <head>
               <hi>Adieu à la Monde.</hi> To the worſhipfull JOHN MAY Eſquire ſenior, Alderman of Lyn.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>WIt, Valour, Riches, Honour, Beauty, Birth,</l>
               <l>Are Baits for Mortals, laid by Stepdame Earth.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="1">
               <head>1.</head>
               <l>Cato for Government the pride of Rome,</l>
               <l>From whom ſo many wholſom Laws did come,</l>
               <l>Who did foretell proud Caeſars tyranny,</l>
               <l>Aegyptian Ptolomy did tell his folly,</l>
               <l>Who if he'd followed his Counſel wiſe,</l>
               <l>He had not failed in his Enterpriſe;</l>
               <l>He that did leade the Romans by the ears,</l>
               <l>And could exhilarate amidſt all feare</l>
               <l>To others; Lo! he ſtabs himſelf, alas!</l>
               <l>Virtue, thou ſtoodſt in need of Chriſtian Grace.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="2">
               <head>2.</head>
               <l>Unconque'd Caeſar that third thouſand Town</l>
               <l>Had taken by aſſault, and had beat down</l>
               <l>Three hundred Nations: a Million</l>
               <l>Of Pris'ners taken; nay, he who had won</l>
               <l>Infinite Battles; 'midſt the Senate grave,</l>
               <l>From violent death, alas! could not him ſave.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="3">
               <head>3.</head>
               <l>Lucullus, who by Victories obtain'd</l>
               <l>'Gainſt potent Kings, a maſs of Gold had gain'd,</l>
               <l>And made the richeſt Triumphs that Rome ſaw,</l>
               <l>Ere while ſhe gave the conquered World her Law.</l>
               <l>He who ſcarce knew his Treaſure, loſt his wits,</l>
               <l>Therefore his grave an haſty poyſon fits.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="4">
               <head>4</head>
               <l>Great Alexander that the World did aw,</l>
               <l>And with his Sword did write the Perſians Law,</l>
               <l>He that did captive Kings, and face their Van,</l>
               <l>That princely iſſued Macedonian,</l>
               <l>At laſt ('twas thought) by poyſon loſt his breath;</l>
               <l>For he that conquers Kings, can't conquer Death.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="5">
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:104586:41"/>
               <head>5.</head>
               <l>Fair Alcibiades whoſe beauteous face,</l>
               <l>Did give unto his actions winning grace,</l>
               <l>Which made King Agis Wife be woon unto</l>
               <l>That which was both a ſhame to grant and do.</l>
               <l>He that was call'd the pleaſant ſweet proſpect,</l>
               <l>Whoſe Beauty like the orient Pearl project,</l>
               <l>Could not prevail with Murtherers venom'd darts,</l>
               <l>Nor yet, alas! with their more cruel hearts.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="6">
               <head>6.</head>
               <l>Pyrrhus deſcended from Achilles brave,</l>
               <l>Whoſe loud-mouth'd fame ſhall never finde a grave,</l>
               <l>One of the nobleſt Families in Greece,</l>
               <l>Succeſſively found valours maſter-piece,</l>
               <l>Was ſlain from off a houſe by a thrown Tile,</l>
               <l>For ſuch a peerleſs Prince a death too vile!</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <head>MEDITATION.</head>
            <lg n="1">
               <head>1.</head>
               <l>Omnipotent Lord! who know'ſt my ſecret thought,</l>
               <l>And before whom ſecrets reveal'd are brought:</l>
               <l>Since thou art omnipotent, I e're ſhall ſtrain,</l>
               <l>To ſhew all mundane things but meerly vain.</l>
               <l>Ile fear to meddle with that Engine wit,</l>
               <l>Becauſe it doth the Enginier of 't hit:</l>
               <l>However Ile not truſt to it, for vain</l>
               <l>Are all things that proceed from man's meer brain.</l>
               <l>Thy wiſer Solomon when he was jolly,</l>
               <l>He plac'd a heaven in that, but found it folly.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="2">
               <head>2.</head>
               <l>Ile fear all Dalilahs, prevent a guſt;</l>
               <l>Deſire to anker ſure, in ſpite of luſt:</l>
               <l>Ile not preſume upon my valour, O!</l>
               <l>How ſhort a way could I in my ſtrength go?</l>
               <l>Thy Sampſon too much truſting to his ſtrength,</l>
               <l>Was overcome, and vilely us'd at length.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="3">
               <head>3:</head>
               <l>What ſhall I ſtrive to catch a bird i'th' air?</l>
               <l>For Riches make them wings and flie affair,</l>
               <l>And <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>arr. Give me not over much my God!</l>
               <l>Wiſe Agurs Prayer is mine, enough for food</l>
               <l>And Rayment; if thou think'ſt fit to give more,</l>
               <l>Some Ile return unto thee by the poor.</l>
               <l>Thou mad'ſt thy Job (the richeſt of the Eaſt)</l>
               <l>Even (for a time) to Vermin vile a Feaſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="4">
               <head>4.</head>
               <l>Ile ſeek not honour, for alas! the man</l>
               <l>That hath it acts but the Comoedian.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="59" facs="tcp:104586:41"/>He holds it but untill the Play is done,</l>
               <l>Perhaps before the Plaudite 'tis gone.</l>
               <l>Thine own dear David, now an honour'd King.</l>
               <l>A Shimei now on him Reproches fling.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="5">
               <head>5.</head>
               <l>Ile grieve not for a wither'd Roſe, Ile ſcorn</l>
               <l>All ſuch things that do die, as ſoon as born.</l>
               <l>Should I ere over-love a face that turns</l>
               <l>To aſhey pale in ſickneſs when it burns?</l>
               <l>An Abſalom was hang'd upon a Tree,</l>
               <l>What Beauty great did men then in him ſee!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="6">
               <head>6.</head>
               <l>I ſcarcely call my Fathers merits mine,</l>
               <l>Good Parents do convince bad Childrens line</l>
               <l>Of their degenerate, depraved acts.</l>
               <l>Except I'm good, what help my Fathers facts?</l>
               <l>A Rehoboam is the more made guilty,</l>
               <l>By his good Fathers, of iniquity.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Wit's weak, Valour doth fail, Riches do flie,</l>
               <l>Honour halts, Beauty fades, and Birth doth lie:</l>
               <l>Therefore (O Lord) I onely crave but thee,</l>
               <l>Let others crave thoſe earthly things for me.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <head>
               <hi>Solomons</hi> Caveat of the Harlot.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>I Take it wiſdom here for to repeat</l>
               <l>Thoſe things of her the Wiſeman doth relate.</l>
               <l>The lips of a ſtrange woman drop as honey,<note place="margin">Prov. 5.3.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Her mouth ſmoother than oil (to get your money)</l>
               <l>Her end as bitter is as ſowr Wormwood,</l>
               <l>Sharper it is than a two-edged Sword.</l>
               <l>Her feet go down to Death, her ſteps to Hell;</l>
               <l>Leaſt thou ſhould'ſt ponder her path of life well,</l>
               <l>Her wayes are moveable, not to be known,</l>
               <l>(And ev'ry one that courteth her's her own.)</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>My Son keep thy ſelf from the evil Woman,<note place="margin">Prov. 6.25.</note>
               </l>
               <l>The flatt'ring tongue of the perverſer Woman.</l>
               <l>After her Beauty luſt not in thine heart,</l>
               <l>Nor let her take thee with her eye-lids art;</l>
               <l>For by a Whore a man is brought to nought,</l>
               <l>And the adultereſs man's life hath ſought.</l>
               <l>Can fire be in th' boſom, and cloths not torn?</l>
               <l>One to tread on hot Coals, his feet not burn?</l>
               <l>So he that to his neighbours wife ere went,</l>
               <l>And touched her, ſhall not be innocent.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="60" facs="tcp:104586:42"/>The window of my houſe I looked thorow,<note place="margin">Prov. 7.7.</note>
               </l>
               <l>And did behold a young man that was ſhallow,</l>
               <l>Paſſing the ſtreets thorow unto her corner,</l>
               <l>He went he way unto the houſe of th' ſcorner.</l>
               <l>In the evening in the half-dark twi-light,</l>
               <l>In the black, dark, diſmall, and dang'rous night.</l>
               <l>And behold! there did meet him a Woman,</l>
               <l>With the attire of a right Harlot on,</l>
               <l>Subtill of heart (ſhe is both loud and ſtubborn,</l>
               <l>Her feet abide not in her houſe, ſhe's gone</l>
               <l>Without, now in the ſtreets (is a ſuborner)</l>
               <l>And ſhe lyeth in wait at ev'ry corner)</l>
               <l>So ſhe caught him, and kiſſed him (ſo ſlim!)</l>
               <l>And with an impudent face ſaid to him,</l>
               <l>I have Peace-offerings with me, but now</l>
               <l>Ev'n this day Sweeteſt have I pay'd my vow,</l>
               <l>Therefore came I to ſeek ſo diligently</l>
               <l>Thy ſweeter face, and lo! Now I have found thee,</l>
               <l>I've deck'd my Bed with Tap'ſtry Coverings,</l>
               <l>With carved Work, fine Linnen, and ſuch things,</l>
               <l>I have perfum'd my Bed (O don't be gone!)</l>
               <l>With pretious Myrrhe, Aloes, and Cynamon:</l>
               <l>Come let us take our fill of Love (my Dear)</l>
               <l>Untill the morning let us ſolace here,</l>
               <l>For the Good man is not at home you ſee,</l>
               <l>(I'm ſure he'll ſtay) he's gone a long journey.</l>
               <l>O of ſuch Whores the deeper ſubtilty!</l>
               <l>And of their ſlaves the great ſimplicity!</l>
               <l>Lord, let thy ſervant rather beg at th' door,</l>
               <l>Then ere inſnared by a damned Whore!</l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>The end of the Divine Poems.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <head>Sickneſs.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>I Feel my ſtrength o'th' ſuddain me to fail,</l>
               <l>I feel inſulting ſickneſs me aſſail;</l>
               <l>Then I think on my ſins, my fleſh ſo frail.</l>
               <l>There is a God!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>I do obſerve my meat, my drink, my air,</l>
               <l>My exerciſes, ſtudy; yet my care</l>
               <l>Prevents not; I may be choak'd with an hair.</l>
               <l>There is a God!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>One hand doth ask the other how it fares,</l>
               <l>(By the Pulſe) mine eye asks m' urine how it ſhares,</l>
               <l>With this diſtemper, while I'm worn with cares;</l>
               <l>Yet thou 'rt my God!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:104586:42"/>
               <l>My fear of Sickneſs doth as much afflict,</l>
               <l>As of fore-paſſed ſickneſs the relict;</l>
               <l>Thus by thy Sergeant is thy ſervant kick'd.</l>
               <l>Strengthen, oh God!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Throw cold water on fire, oh this is jolly,</l>
               <l>This is thy ſervants wonted peeviſh folly,</l>
               <l>Wrap a hot feaver in cold melancholy.</l>
               <l>Make wiſe, oh God!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>I cannot hold, oh Lord, glory I muſt,</l>
               <l>Of th'holy Ghoſts temple I am ſome duſt,</l>
               <l>No marble is ſo precious, I muſt</l>
               <l>Remember God!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The remedy's as bad as the diſeaſe,</l>
               <l>Purging a weak man, oh how can this pleaſe!</l>
               <l>Or how can this, oh Lord, thy ſervant eaſe!</l>
               <l>Yet there's a God!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>I take down drugs, then wormwood bitter fare,</l>
               <l>As loathſome as the loathſomeſt that are,</l>
               <l>Liſten to all receipts both near and farre:</l>
               <l>Which bleſs oh God!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Yet thou art juſt in all thy acts alone,</l>
               <l>Who ſo oft lead me for my ſins to groane;</l>
               <l>As for my pain in ſickneſs I have ſhowne,</l>
               <l>Pardon oh God!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>My Parents would not let ſervants correct me,</l>
               <l>And let not Satan, oh God, e'r afflict me,</l>
               <l>Not by Satan would I afflicted be:</l>
               <l>Grant this, oh God!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Yet Lord, how much have I been a miſtaker,</l>
               <l>And almoſt had forgotten God my maker!</l>
               <l>Oh therefore am I of this Pain partaker:</l>
               <l>Forget oh God!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The Bell that toles for ſome departing ſoul,</l>
               <l>Makes me think I may taſte of Death's brimm'd boul;</l>
               <l>And then, oh Lord, how can I it controul?</l>
               <l>Make fit, oh God!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>I ſtudy not how my ſoul firſt came in,</l>
               <l>But how 'twas guilty of moſt hainous ſin,</l>
               <l>To ſtudy of its end I doe begin:</l>
               <l>Oh help, ô God!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Wih St <hi>Auguſtin</hi> this ſhall be my ſtation,</l>
               <l>I doe deſire to know my tranſmigration,</l>
               <l>And that I certain be of thy ſalvation:</l>
               <l>Which grant, oh God!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The ſoul o'th' man that dy'd I prayed for,</l>
               <l>And for to judge him damn'd I doe abhor;</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="62" facs="tcp:104586:43"/>But charitably think him ſaved; for</l>
               <l>Thou'rt good, oh God!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The body whence the ſoul ſo loath did part,</l>
               <l>T'exchange for heav'n, is ſo that now all Art</l>
               <l>Acknowledg muſt they ſet her out in part:</l>
               <l>Poor fleſh, oh God!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Who would not be affected much to ſee,</l>
               <l>A morning River ſweet that ran clearly,</l>
               <l>A kennel grow, and to run muddily?</l>
               <l>Such is man, God!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Then hopes of cure my heavy heart doe raiſe,</l>
               <l>Oh open then my lips to ſhew thy praiſe,</l>
               <l>For Lord, my duller fleſh skils not thy wayes:</l>
               <l>Almighty God!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Oh how I then did think to lead a life,</l>
               <l>Lord, like a member of thy dearer wife</l>
               <l>Thy Church, which ever grant be void of ſtrife:</l>
               <l>Thou peacefull God!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Theſe holy thoughts confirm thou in mine heart,</l>
               <l>That I may praiſe thy name with utmoſt art,</l>
               <l>And that I may from thy Laws never ſtart:</l>
               <l>Grant this, oh God!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Lord keep me from a ſad relapſe, I crave;</l>
               <l>Then ſhalt thy ſervant ſtrength and pleaſure have:</l>
               <l>But, oh Lord, let me not thy ſtrength to wave:</l>
               <l>Oh Lord my God!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>For 'twill be ſad to run the courſe again,</l>
               <l>To purge, to ſweat, and to doe all in vain;</l>
               <l>Doe thou thy bleſſings therefore on me rain:</l>
               <l>My gracious God!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Let not thy ſervant poor e'r be relapſed,</l>
               <l>Into thoſe ſins which are truly repealed,</l>
               <l>And thou, oh Lord, haſt fully pardoned:</l>
               <l>Thou art my God!</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <head>The PROTECTION.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <l>To th'Admirall, Vice- or Reer-Admirall;</l>
                  <l>Renowned Captains unto each and all.</l>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <l>WE greet you well: and will that this our Son</l>
            <l>By you nor yours no violence be done</l>
            <l>His Merchandize, or ought pertains unto him:</l>
            <l>For if you doe, you doe not only undoe him,</l>
            <l>But doe affront our high authority,</l>
            <l>And ſhall doe by us moſt unworthily.</l>
            <l>
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:104586:43"/>You ſons of Neptune, hereby we doe charge</l>
            <l>You, if you take him, that you him diſcharge</l>
            <l>And his goods free; or if you be ſo ill,</l>
            <l>As to deny't, then anſwer't at your perill;</l>
            <l>For be it known unto you from this Place,</l>
            <l>He's order'd for to trade in Wit and Grace.</l>
            <l>We three, and thrice-three ſtraitly doe command</l>
            <l>The proudeſt of you not to lay your hand</l>
            <l>Upon this our dear Son, from Rupert brave,</l>
            <l>Unto the meaneſt thrommet, or baſe ſlave;</l>
            <l>For by great Jove our Father, and our Mother</l>
            <l>Fair Venus; your neglect we will not ſmother.</l>
            <l>Great Pallas, and Minerva we'll inform,</l>
            <l>If he abuſe this our choice Microcoſm;</l>
            <l>Then we'll inform our mother Mnemoſyne;</l>
            <l>And ye ſhall never taſte Nectarean wine:</l>
            <l>But ſhall be puniſh'd by the puniſhment</l>
            <l>Great Jove for ſuch offenders did Invent.</l>
            <closer>
               <signed>Giv'n at Olympus high, Signed and ſealed by <hi>And at Parnaſſus Hill Sign'd by our ſacred Quill.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
               <list>
                  <head>The Graces</head>
                  <item>Agiaia</item>
                  <item>Thalia</item>
                  <item>Euphroſyne</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>The Muſes</head>
                  <item>Clio</item>
                  <item>Melpomene</item>
                  <item>Thalia</item>
                  <item>Euterpo</item>
                  <item>Terpſichore</item>
                  <item>Erato</item>
                  <item>Calliope</item>
                  <item>Urania</item>
                  <item>Polymnia</item>
               </list>
            </postscript>
         </div>
         <div type="conclusion">
            <head>CONCL<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SION.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>I Know I ſhall be counted madd and rude</l>
               <l>By the wilde, giddy-headed multitude,</l>
               <l>To write in ſuch ſtrange dayes, for now men ſink</l>
               <l>Their judgments, having drown'd them firſt with drink.</l>
               <l>Envie and Ignorance, I'm confident</l>
               <l>Will ſcarcely well this work of mine reſent.</l>
               <l>Amongſt the Wits 'tis Epidemicall,</l>
               <l>On their Rivals Momus-like for to fall.</l>
               <l>Like to the ignorant no foe to wit,</l>
               <l>And he's condemn'd that do'nt each humor fit.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="64" facs="tcp:104586:44"/>One would have obſcene Poëms, th'other plain,</l>
               <l>A third one writing in a lofty ſtrain;</l>
               <l>One tedious things affects; another ſhort;</l>
               <l>Another ſays Verſe onely ſhould make ſport.</l>
               <l>Some, that he is no Poet, holds no Quill,</l>
               <l>Except he equal Homer, or great Virgill;</l>
               <l>Some, none ſhould write, except like Scaliger,</l>
               <l>Who could in thirty Languages confer:</l>
               <l>Or ſuch, as Ariſtarchus, that (no leſs)</l>
               <l>Two hundred Books could fit unto the Preſs.</l>
               <l>Or he whoſe mem'ry is full as terſe</l>
               <l>As Seneca's, who could at firſt rehearſe</l>
               <l>Hundreds of words after the hearing; then</l>
               <l>I think no mortall men ſhould uſe a Pen.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But I am like Heraclitus; no Tutor</l>
               <l>In Cham, or Ox, was e'r my Co-adjutor,</l>
               <l>Wherefore the truer Poet ſome men ſay;</l>
               <l>But they their ignorances doe betray.</l>
               <l>Other affairs command this Book ſo ſmall,</l>
               <l>And my late ſickneſſe cruſh'd the growth withall,</l>
               <l>And made the Copy the worſe writ; I fear</l>
               <l>By that the Printer will abuſe the Reader,</l>
               <l>And much more me, ſomewhat my noble Friends,</l>
               <l>Who me their quaint Encomiaſticks lends</l>
               <l>Unto my Book. I have of this a ſence,</l>
               <l>There's no diſpute againſt Experience,</l>
               <l>And at the Preſs I cannot be; wherefore:</l>
               <l>Good Printer, let your care appear the more.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>I ſeldom uſe more Letters then there's need,</l>
               <l>With witty, learned Howell, and th'more ſpeed,</l>
               <l>With much more eaſe is found; wherefore excuſe</l>
               <l>The humor (ſince 'tis lawfull) of my Muſe.</l>
               <l>And I am tyred in re-writing, ſee!</l>
               <l>The reaſon is, becauſe 'tis old to me.</l>
               <l>Now without malice, I doe wiſh't to bee</l>
               <l>To all e'r-laſting, (Stationer but to thee.)</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>What ſhall I never quiet be? Now news,</l>
               <l>That I doe ſuch a friend in Verſe abuſe,</l>
               <l>In daring for to conſolate in Verſe</l>
               <l>After an action that requir'd Cypreſſe,</l>
               <l>Rather then Bayes. Now that I writ my ſelf</l>
               <l>Moſt famous Poet, when the prating Elf</l>
               <l>I ſhrewdly judge, can ſcarcely read Engliſh.</l>
               <l>Lord, free me from theſe prating fools I wiſh!</l>
               <l>Or elſe in theſe things let this be my ſence,</l>
               <l>"Thou tak'ſt a Text, and preacheſt Patience.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:104586:44"/>
               <l>Here's one with Swearing makes the room to ſhake,</l>
               <l>Saying, O fool, why doſt thou theſe pains take?</l>
               <l>Is this the way to grow rich? oh thou fond man!</l>
               <l>Come hither, chear thy ſpirits with a full Cann.</l>
               <l>Will Verſe pay debts, or will your lofty Rimes</l>
               <l>Mount you to place of truſt in theſe our times?</l>
               <l>Oh the injuſtice of conceited Owls,</l>
               <l>That think none godly, but thoſe that wear Cowls!</l>
               <l>None wiſe, but thoſe that with his wit doe jump,</l>
               <l>Although for it he lab'rouſly doth pump.</l>
               <l>Let thoſe that hunt the ſtately Stagg with hounds,</l>
               <l>Not be (unjuſtly kept) in th'Shepherd's bounds.</l>
               <l>Thoſe that Hawking delights, not be impeded</l>
               <l>From that refreſhment which great Princes uſed;</l>
               <l>Thoſe that in catching ſilly Fiſh delight</l>
               <l>Be hindred from it; Nor that love the flight</l>
               <l>Of a broad Arrow; Thoſe that learn Defence,</l>
               <l>Or thoſe that love to pleaſ the hearing Sen e.</l>
               <l>Then whence I pray you can a man ſurmiſe</l>
               <l>That 'tis unfitting thus to Poëtiſe?</l>
               <l>If ye pleaſe Zoiliſts to court your Whore,</l>
               <l>Why ſhould I ſtop you entring at the door?</l>
               <l>If you doe fight as ſtoutly as game-Cocks,</l>
               <l>What helps, if they doe pay you with a Pox?</l>
               <l>If Swearing pleaſe your humors, and if good?</l>
               <l>Doth me, why doe you uſe this carping mood?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Some cavill at my Readings fruits; yet ſee</l>
               <l>From many ſlowers hony's got by th' Bee;</l>
               <l>And the Spider, whoſe work is all her own,</l>
               <l>As worthleſs by the Broom away is thrown.</l>
               <l>Some that things Morall with Divine are mix'd,</l>
               <l>When ſome men loves on th'Book by that are fix'd;</l>
               <l>And ſeeking (perhaps) for Verſe that is fine,</l>
               <l>May be made amorous of Verſe Divine.</l>
               <l>Laſtly, Readers, my Muſings I'll amend</l>
               <l>If ye accept this, or elſe here's</l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
            <closer>Soli Deo Sola Gloria.</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="list">
            <pb facs="tcp:104586:45"/>
            <head>The Alphabeticall Table.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="A"/> THe Author to his Book in four tongues, next the Epiſtle to the Reader.</item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="C"/> Content page 42</item>
               <item>Concluſion page 63</item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="D"/> Drunkenneſſe page 16</item>
               <item>The Devil-Pope page 14</item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="E"/> Elegy on one HUNT a Groom, ſlain cowardly by his fellow-Servant page 32</item>
               <item>Epigrams and Epitaphs page 5</item>
               <item>Epithalamium to Mr. G. H. page 9</item>
               <item>Epiſtle to Sir R. S. page 6</item>
               <item>Elegy to my Yoak-fellow page 35</item>
               <item>Elegy to Brother T. S. on the death of his childe page 31</item>
               <item>Elegie on the Shipwrack of J.O. and his company page 40</item>
               <item>Epitaph on Tho. Slany Major of Lyn page 28</item>
               <item>Elegy and Epitaph on my Daughter AMY. page 33</item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="F"/> Farewell to the World page 10</item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="I"/> The Inn page 36</item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="L"/> The Lords-day page 46</item>
               <item>Long-ſuffering page 40</item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="O"/> The Opinion page 44</item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="P"/> Pain page 41</item>
               <item>The Protection page 62</item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="R"/> The Repentant page 51</item>
               <item>The Rimer routed page 21</item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="S"/> Sickneſs page 60</item>
               <item>The Sinner page 47</item>
               <item>The Storm and Calm page 1</item>
               <item>Song at the Authors laſt comming out of Germany page 7</item>
               <item>Solomon's Caveat of the Harlot page 59</item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="T"/> The Travels page 25</item>
            </list>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
